<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true relation of the murders committed in the parish of Clunne in the county of Salop by Enoch ap Evan upon the bodies of his mother and brother, with the causes moving him thereunto. Wherein is examined and refuted a certaine booke written upon the same subject, by P. Studley, entituled the Looking glasse of schisme. Also an appendix in further defence of this relation, wherein are examined the most material passages added in the second edition of the said Looking-glasse, wherby the author, vainely sheweth his desire to maintaine and excuse his erroneous reports in the former edition of his booke. By Richar [sic] More Esquire. Printed by order of a committee of the Honourable House of Commons now assembled in Parliament.</title>
            <author>More, Richard, d. 1643.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 122 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 89 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51322</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M2685</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R214234</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99826437</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99826437</idno>
            <idno type="VID">30840</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51322)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 30840)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1765:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true relation of the murders committed in the parish of Clunne in the county of Salop by Enoch ap Evan upon the bodies of his mother and brother, with the causes moving him thereunto. Wherein is examined and refuted a certaine booke written upon the same subject, by P. Studley, entituled the Looking glasse of schisme. Also an appendix in further defence of this relation, wherein are examined the most material passages added in the second edition of the said Looking-glasse, wherby the author, vainely sheweth his desire to maintaine and excuse his erroneous reports in the former edition of his booke. By Richar [sic] More Esquire. Printed by order of a committee of the Honourable House of Commons now assembled in Parliament.</title>
                  <author>More, Richard, d. 1643.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[22], 155, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by T.B. for P. Stephens &amp; C. Meredith at the golden Lyon in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1641.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: A true relation of Enoch ap Evan.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Evan, Enoch ap, d. 1633 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Studley, Peter, 1587 or 8-1648. --  Looking-glasse of schisme --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Murder --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:30840:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:30840:1"/>
            <p>A True relation of the <hi>Murders</hi> committed in the <hi>Pariſh</hi> of <hi>Clunne</hi> in the County of <hi>Salop</hi> by <hi>Enoch ap Evan</hi> upon the Bodies of his <hi>Mother</hi> and <hi>Brother,</hi> with the Cauſes moving him thereunto.</p>
            <p>Wherein is examined and refuted a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Booke written upon the ſame Subject, by P. STUDLEY, Entituled the <hi>Looking glaſſe</hi> of <hi>SCHISME.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alſo an Appendix in further defence of this Relation, wherein are examined the moſt material Paſſages added in the Second Edition of the ſaid LOOKING-GLASSE, wherby the Author vainely ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>weth his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to maintaine and excuſe his er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneous Reports in the former Edition of his Booke.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> RICHAR MORE <hi>Eſquire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed by Order of a Committee of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Honourable Houſe of Commons now Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in Parliament.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T.B.</hi> for <hi>P. Stephens</hi> &amp; <hi>C. Meredith</hi> at the golden Lyon in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1641.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="printer_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:30840:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:30840:3"/>
            <head>The Printer to the Reader.</head>
            <p>VVHeras the enſuing trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe referreth to the Pages of the former Edition of the <hi>Looking-glaſſe,</hi> of Schiſm; This is to give notice that both editions (for ſubſtance) doe agree to the <hi>35.</hi> pag; and there beginneth the eleventh Section, wherein <hi>Maſter Studley</hi> inſerteth that <hi>violent love paſſion, which befell Enoch</hi> (the day and night before he committed theſe <hi>Murders</hi>) which being omitted in the former edition occaſioned in the ſecond, an encreaſe of onely foure leaves, ſo in this ſmall diſtance is likely to be found whatſoever this Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hath reference unto, after the ſaid <hi>35</hi> pag. This I thought con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient to be certified in this place for the eaſe of ſuch as have either of the two editions of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Studleys</hi> booke.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:30840:3"/>
            <head>An advertiſement to the <hi>Reader</hi> touching the Enſuing <hi>Relation, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the occaſion of Printing thereof this preſent yeare</hi> 1641. <hi>and how hitherto ſuppreſſed.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Gentle <hi>Reader,</hi>
               </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O the enſuing Diſcourſe the ſtile of the <hi>Prophet Iſaiah,</hi> Cap. 37.3. may be applyed, <hi>the children came to the birth, but there was no ſtrength
<pb facs="tcp:30840:4"/>to bring forth.</hi> This re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation though at firſt not ſo intended, was made ready for the Preſſe in the yeare 1635 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd being then tende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the view of the Licencer who gave ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation for the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of Maſter <hi>Studleys Looking GLASSE</hi> of Schiſme, it was for that time by him rejected. No better acceptance could this Truth then finde, Truth muſt ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bee ſuppreſt than the falſehood of that Glaſſe bee diſcovered.
<pb facs="tcp:30840:4"/>The Author of the <hi>Looking-Glaſſe</hi> preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to ſet forth the diſobedience of Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformiſts againſt Royall Majeſty, and the laws of our <hi>Church</hi> doubtleſſe, Noncormi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and diſobedience to juſt commands are to be ſearched out and brought forth to deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved puniſhment. But experience teacheth that whilſt that angry Author by his falſe glaſſe laboured to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent Nonconfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie to bee the onely
<pb facs="tcp:30840:5"/>cauſe of thoſe execra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Murders commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by <hi>Enoch ap Evan,</hi> hee hath thereby not convinced but harden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed many that waver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and ſcandalized others who better knew their duties to juſt lawes.</p>
            <p>Theſe and other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious conſequences of this deceitful Glaſſe being conſidered by diverſe worthy mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of this preſent Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Aſſembly in Parliament, who well knowing this rejected
<pb facs="tcp:30840:5"/>Relation had diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the true circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of theſe deplo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable murders, by dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence in examining all perſons reputed to have any competent knowledge of the ſaid <hi>Enoch</hi> and his diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolate frinds, they have now called it forth.</p>
            <p>An occaſion of my travell therein was obedience to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of thoſe Iudges, by whoſe ſentence the <hi>murderer</hi> was condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to die, and his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to be hanged up in
<pb facs="tcp:30840:6"/>Chaines, for ſhortly after the execution of that ſentence, the ſaid body being to the great affront of Iuſtice ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly taken downe from the Gibbet and conveyed away; thoſe Iudges required my ſervice, (amongſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers the Iuſtices of that County) for the diſcovery of the offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders. And having here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by informed my ſelfe, I did examine thoſe cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances of fact, whereupon Maſter <hi>Studley</hi> had framed his
<pb facs="tcp:30840:6"/>pretended <hi>Looking-Glaſſe of Schiſme,</hi> and finding the falſhood thereof I compoſed the enſuing Relation, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending my ſelfe thereunto deeply obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, as well for vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of my Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourhood as the ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of ſuch as deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the Truth of this accident. In purſuance wherof I preſented one Copy of this enſuing Relation to the Biſhop of <hi>Hereford,</hi> in whoſe Dioceſſe the murders were committed. Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:30840:7"/>Copy I preſented to the <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Lichfield</hi> and <hi>Coventry,</hi> in whoſe Dioces the Author of the <hi>Looking-glaſſe,</hi> then &amp; now liveth. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards I was moved to commend it to the Preſſe for more pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like ſatisfaction. The ſucceſſe whereof is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore related. All which proceedings being likewiſe knowne to the forementioned wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy members in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and a Comit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee being aſſigned to take information of
<pb facs="tcp:30840:7"/>the complaints againſt refuſing of Licence for printing lawful books, the denyall of this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation was particularly queſtioned by ſome of the ſaid <hi>Committee;</hi> the reaſons given for the deniall being ſlender, By the Vote of the ſaid Comittee this Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was ordered to bee Printed.</p>
            <p>And thus, Gentle Reader, thou haſt a plain account of what I have promiſed in this advertiſement, the uſes which I conceive may
<pb facs="tcp:30840:8"/>be rightly made of this ſad occaſion, I have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt in the twentie ſeventh Section of this relation: whereunto in reference to that vehemency which the Author of the <hi>Looking-glaſſe</hi> manifeſteth in his anſwer to certaine cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations againſt his booke (moſt likely to be of his own compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing) I ſhall here adde the words of <hi>Salomon, Eccleſ.</hi> 7.9, 10. <hi>Bee not hasty in thy ſpirit to be angry, for thou doſt not enquire wiſely, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:30840:8"/>this.</hi> That alſo of our Saviour is not to be forgotten, <hi>Luke</hi> 13.4, 5. <hi>thoſe eighteene on whom the Towre of</hi> Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loam <hi>fell, and ſlew them, thinke yee that they were ſinners above all men that dwelt in Jeruſalem? J tell you Nay: but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept yee repent, yee ſhall all likewiſe periſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo I commend to thy view the relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as it was prepared for the Preſſe in the yeare 1635. where take notice of what follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb facs="tcp:30840:9"/>touching the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and Edition of the <hi>Looking-Glaſſe,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto this relation hath reference.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:30840:9"/>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Deſire thoſe to whoſe hands this enſuing Relation may come, to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, that it hath reference to the firſt printed <hi>Look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-GLASSE</hi> of <hi>Schiſme,</hi> and to the pages of that Booke which is ſince
<pb facs="tcp:30840:10"/>reprinted, with ſome additions, alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and an anſwer to certaine crimina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, or objections of the Author of his owne framing: which I take not up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me to medle with further, then wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they are contrary or contradictory to what in this of mine is ſet forth: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in J have ſet downe
<pb facs="tcp:30840:10"/>the ground and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority upon which it is warranted, and have named the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties upon whoſe teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony the truth will reſt: as <hi>Maſter Eraſmus Powell</hi> Vicar of <hi>Clunne,</hi> who hath peruſed my whole Relation, and hath ſubſcribed that Coppy which J keep, testifying, that thoſe things in and about
<pb facs="tcp:30840:11"/>which I uſe his name or referre my ſelfe to his knowledge, are truly ſet downe by mee, and received from him. So hath <hi>Iohn Howels</hi> the brother in law of <hi>Enoch,</hi> whom <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Studley</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth <hi>Iohn Powell,</hi> in the confirmation of whoſe words hee confeſſeth the life and Truth of that
<pb facs="tcp:30840:11"/>Hiſtory is really con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taind, as is ſet down, page the eighth, of his anſwer mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned aforeſaid. And in like manner of all the reſt, upon whom any materiall point of contradiction reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. So that what is in difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene us, will bee apparent by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords, acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, manifeſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction
<pb facs="tcp:30840:12"/>in the <hi>Looking-glaſſe</hi> it ſelfe, or witneſses ſuch as wee both a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree upon. All which will bee evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to him that ſhall diligently com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare them: and which I leave to the judgement of the conſiderate Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, the maine ſcope of mine intention herein being peace
<pb facs="tcp:30840:2"/>with truth, which is ever Prayed for by</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>The true lover Thereof</hi>
Richard More.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>LINTEY</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>29.</hi> Iune <hi>1635.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:30840:12"/>
            <head>A True relation of the Murders commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by <hi>Enoch ap Evan</hi> upon the bodies of his <hi>Mother</hi> and <hi>Brother.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>SECTION. I.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Ruth is Gods, and He hath bound man to Manifeſt the ſame if con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed, and to vindicate her if wronged: and whoſoever
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:30840:13"/>ſhall either Conceale or wrong her, or hinder the manifeſtation, or vindicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereof ſhall offend. The ſerious conſideration wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, hath moved me to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake this briefe enſuing treatiſe, for the more full diſcovery of the truth, (in part) as yet not generally knowne, and to rectifie the conceits of many, who have beene abuſed (as the beſt may be) by falſe reports. The matter it ſelfe (though both the party by whom, and the place where it was done, were obſcure) is very notorious and remarkeable, and ſuch as many not onely of the Vulgar ſort, but emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent perſons have taken no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of, and ſo much more by reaſon of a Booke publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:30840:13"/>intituled the <hi>Looking Glaſſe of Schiſme:</hi> wherein (as the Author pretendeth) by a briefe narration of the execrable Murders done by <hi>Enoch ap Evan</hi> a downe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right <hi>Separatiſt,</hi> on the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of his <hi>Mother</hi> and <hi>Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> with the cauſe moving him thereunto, the diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of that Sect againſt <hi>Royall Majeſtie,</hi> and the <hi>Laws</hi> of our <hi>Church,</hi> is plainely ſet forth, be <hi>Peter Studley Maſter of Artes,</hi> and <hi>Miniſter</hi> of <hi>Gods Word</hi> in <hi>Shrewſbury.</hi> That this Murder was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted is true, and no waie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> doubted of. The queſtion is what ſhould be the cauſe moving him thereto? And what kinde of people inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited the <hi>Neighbourhood</hi> where thoſe Murders were
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:30840:14"/>committed? It is confident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affirmed that hee was a <hi>Puritan,</hi> that <hi>Puritaniſme</hi> was the cauſe moving him to this Murder, for which he had judgement to dye, and his Body was hanged upon a <hi>Gibbet</hi> in <hi>Chaines;</hi> and moreover, that they were <hi>Puritans</hi> who tooke him downe from the <hi>Gib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet,</hi> and that he had beene by politicke ſeducements drawne into thoſe opinions, (<hi>Looking-Glaſſe</hi> page one hundred thirty ſeven) ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperate and raging in their furious cruelty. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon I laboured to enforme my ſelfe, and was required by Authority (amongſt others) to ſearch out the truth, and to diſcover the Parties who had taken
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:30840:14"/>downe the body of <hi>Enoch</hi> from the <hi>Gibbet.</hi> Which being diſcovered, I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the ſeverall paſſages to writing, wherewith I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted a Miniſter in the Neighbourhood. He redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced my Papers into a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodicall confutation of thoſe errours and untruths, which are moſt palpable, and indeed intollerable. It being finiſhed, was inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for the Preſſe, yet not permitted. When I percea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved untruth ſo much ſtill to prevaile, many abuſed, my neighbourhood about <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops Caſtle</hi> injured, and ſuch ill uſe made of ſuch a fearefull example; I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaved my ſelfe deepely obliged to enforme others in the truth, vindicate my
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:30840:15"/>neighbours, and to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade others to make bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter uſe of this lamentable accident. And to that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, having reviſed mine owne papers, have digeſted them into this Hiſtoricall narration: wherein I doe acknowledge more want of ability to ſet truth forth to the View of the Learned, then of an honeſt and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right heart to diſcover her, though naked and without ornaments. And herein I ſhall differ from the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon receaved opinion of thoſe that are more remote from this part of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, concerning the <hi>Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taniſme</hi> wherewith this wretch was charged: and perhaps for the ſame I ſhall be ſuſpected to be Puritani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:30840:15"/>or at leaſt to Patronize <hi>Puritaniſme,</hi> both which being taken in the ſence of <hi>Schiſme</hi> or non-conformity I ſolemnely diſavowe, and ſeriouſly proteſt, that I have alwayes diſliked Non-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity, and both in judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and practice have conformed my ſelfe unto the Orders and Diſcipline of this Church of <hi>England,</hi> and eſpecially in that parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular of kneeling ſo farre, as, that if our Church had left the geſture to be uſed in the bleſſed <hi>Sacrament</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>determined, I would have made choice of that geſture of Kneeling before all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, as the moſt reverend, and fitteſt to be uſed in that holy Action, wherein wee come ſo neere unto our <hi>God.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:30840:16"/>
               <head>Sect. 2.</head>
               <p>Herein my ſpeciall aime (according to the truth of my knowledge) being, to free the neighbourhood of <hi>Biſhops Caſtle</hi> (wherein I live and have beſtowed my time) from the falſe and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famous <hi>aſperſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ns</hi> of <hi>Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taniſme</hi> and <hi>Non-conformity;</hi> I ſet my ſelfe on worke to make this true relation en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing, touching the eſtate of the ſaid <hi>Enoch ap Evan,</hi> the Sonne of <hi>Edward ap Evan</hi> of <hi>Shadwall,</hi> in the Pariſh of <hi>Clunne,</hi> in the County of <hi>Salop,</hi> where he lived all the time from his Birth; and to ſhew how he was thought of by the neighbours about <hi>Biſhops Caſtle, no Puritans,</hi>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:30840:16"/>though ſo tearmed by the Author of the <hi>Looking-Glaſſe</hi> page 102.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>Sect. 3.</head>
               <p>It is certaine hee was a young man of no great abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities for learning, he could onely read Engliſh, he was thrifty and given to no vice, whereof any publicke notice was taken; hee did diligently frequent his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh Church of <hi>Clunne</hi> upon <hi>Sundaies</hi> and <hi>Holy daies,</hi> to heare Divine Service, and was ſeldome abſent from the beginning of Prayers: he very ſeldome went to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other Pariſh Church up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any weeke dayes: hee was not knowne to reaſon
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:30840:17"/>of any matters of contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie in religion, as being above his capacity, which was very meane, as the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the <hi>Looking-Glaſſe</hi> often confeſſeth calling him <hi>ignorant Dolte, of meane Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, able onely to read Engliſh,</hi> &amp;c. He was ſo farre from travelling abroad to heare Sermons, or to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint himſelfe with any Preacher, that I cannot find out that he was knowne of any Miniſter that dwelt but three Miles from him, He ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther gave himſelfe to ſolita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rines, eſpecially in his later time: and as is confeſſed in the foreſaid book p. 21. being of a ſwarthy complexion under the Predominance of the humour of Melancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſo hee carried himſelfe
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:30840:17"/>ſullenly and Cynically, in ſo much that his friends feared that he began to be diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted a yere and more before he committed that horrible murder of his <hi>Mother</hi> and <hi>Brother;</hi> and thereupon was let blood by the Barbour Chirurgion of <hi>Biſhops Caſtle</hi> by name <hi>William Griffiths,</hi> which blood letting for that yeare, it ſeemes, ſtayed the breaking forth of that humour into any notorious obſervation: but not halfe a yeare before the Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der committed, in a very cold ſeaſon of Froſt and Show, he was ſeene to ſtand barefooted and bare legged in the middeſt of a running brooke, which with the force of the ſtreame, his face being up the ſame, did wet
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:30840:18"/>him to the middle; his hat he held before his face, as if he were praying. Maſter <hi>Clunne</hi> of <hi>Clunne</hi> a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in the neighbourhood ryding by the place with his wife, conceived him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he came neere, to have beene a naturall foole, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Iohn</hi> of <hi>Acton,</hi> dwelling not farre from thence, untill his wife tould him that it was <hi>Enoch ap Evan;</hi> the gentleman then ſeeing who it was, perſwaded him to to regard his health, to put on his Hoſe and Shoes, and to go home to warme him, and that hee would take a more convenient place to pray in. And this is the truth of that which the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the <hi>Looking-Glaſſe</hi> hath ſo much miſtaken in
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:30840:18"/>his eleventh page both in the perſons and the matter, multiplying words as a falſe Glaſſe doth faces, and of a little tale tould him, by his Rhetoricall additions maketh a long ſtory. <hi>Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Tanner</hi> juſtifyeth that he tould this to Maſter <hi>Studly</hi> in this manner, and not as he hath related it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>Sect. 4.</head>
               <p>After this at Eaſter fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, <hi>Enoch</hi> with his <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Mother</hi> and <hi>Brother</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to receive the <hi>Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> at their Pariſh Church of <hi>Clunne</hi> aforeſaid, he reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently in outward ſhew re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the Bread from Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Powels</hi> hand, who is the Vicar of <hi>Clunne</hi> alowed
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:30840:19"/>by the Author of the <hi>Look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-Glaſſe</hi> to be a reverend and aged Divine page forty ſeven, and indeed hee is a Maſter of Arts of an ancient ſtanding, the rurall Deane of that Deanery of <hi>Clunne,</hi> and a Surrogate to the Chancellour of the Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of <hi>Hereford:</hi>) but when the aſſiſtant by name Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Robert Barret</hi> following Maſter <hi>Powell</hi> to deliver the Wine) came to <hi>Enoch,</hi> he found him not prepared by kneeling downe, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he called upon him to kneele; <hi>Enoch</hi> bad him fill <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Cup with Wine, and although there was in the Cup more then uſually o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers drinke, or that he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe had uſed to drinke, yet notwithſtanding the Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:30840:19"/>filled the Cup, and comming backe to <hi>Enoch,</hi> he bowed his knee, and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the Cup dranke all the Wine within a very little. Now this ſtrange alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from his former uſuall manner being obſerved in <hi>Enoch,</hi> the opinion that he began to be diſtracted en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed ſo, as the ſaid Vicar of <hi>Clunne</hi> thereupon ſent Maſter <hi>Barret</hi> to <hi>Enochs</hi> fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to adviſe him to looke to his ſonne <hi>Enoch,</hi> and to procure ſome help for him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>Sect. 5.</head>
               <p>After this in <hi>May</hi> next before he committed theſe Murders, <hi>Enoch</hi> came to one <hi>Iohn Lewis</hi> a Smith in <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:30840:20"/>Caſtle</hi> a man of good credit, with whom one Maſter <hi>Gravenor</hi> a Scrive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſojourned, and intreated <hi>Iohn Lewis</hi> to helpe him to agree with Maſter <hi>Grave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor</hi> to teach him to write better, for hee could not then write legibly, and they agreed that for five ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings the ſaid Maſter <hi>Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venor</hi> ſhould teach him, <hi>Iohn Lewis</hi> admitted <hi>Enoch</hi> into his houſe with Maſter <hi>Gravenor</hi> where <hi>Enoch</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued about a fortnight. There was then in <hi>Biſhops Castle</hi> one Maſter <hi>Iohn Moore</hi> a Schoolmaſter, who came to the houſe of <hi>Iohn Lewis,</hi> and deſired the ſaid Maſter <hi>Gravenor</hi> to ſhew him his proſpective glaſſe, upon ſight whereof the ſaid Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:30840:20"/>
                  <hi>Moore,</hi> Maſter <hi>Grave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, Enoch ap Evan,</hi> and <hi>Iohn Lewis</hi> went into the yard or backeſide of the ſaid <hi>Iohn Lewis</hi> his houſe, where all of them made uſe of the proſpective, Maſter <hi>Moore</hi> and Maſter <hi>Gravenor</hi> thence diſcerning through the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Sheepe upon a Hill called <hi>Biſhops Moate,</hi> but <hi>Iohn Lewis</hi> could not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne any thing through the ſame; <hi>Enoch</hi> looked through it alſo, but ſaid no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all to them. That night there lodged in the houſe one that brought To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bacco to ſel, and ſome other Schollers: and in the night when they were all quiet in Bed, <hi>Iohn Lewis</hi> heard one comming downe the Staires from the Roome
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:30840:21"/>where <hi>Enoch</hi> lay, and hee called and asked who is up there? <hi>Enoch</hi> anſwered, I am here: whereupon <hi>Iohn Lewis</hi> roſe out of his bed to come to him, and found <hi>Enoch</hi> much diſtempered, and to utter imperfect ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. <hi>Iohn Lewis</hi> perſwaded him to goe to bed, and to take his reſt: <hi>Enoch</hi> would not, but ſaid, did you ſee that villaine my Maſter (meaning Maſter <hi>Gravenor,</hi> the Scrivener) how he hath betrayed me, and conjured the Tobacco-ſeller to come from <hi>Ireland</hi> to kill mee? And the ſaid <hi>Enoch</hi> being in his Shirt, deſired <hi>Iohn Lewis</hi> to lend him a ſuite of Apparell, and would not be perſwaded to fetch his own out of the Chamber. <hi>Iohn
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:30840:21"/>Lewis</hi> endeavoured to ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie <hi>Enoch</hi> that hee did but dreame, and that hee was miſtaken: and the better to worke upon <hi>Enoch, Iohn Lewis</hi> cauſed his Wife to to ariſe, and got <hi>Enoch</hi> to come with him into his bed, and <hi>Iohns</hi> wife being riſen, made firſt a Poſſet and afterwards an Alebrew for <hi>Enoch,</hi> and at laſt after ſome ſpeeches of <hi>Enoch</hi> which were Non-ſence he fell on ſleepe. Hereupon <hi>Iohn Lewis</hi> and his wife (having heard before that <hi>Enoch</hi> was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined to Lunacy) then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded it was true which they had herd. On the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row <hi>Enoch</hi> aroſe and began to write, but it was not long before <hi>Iohn Lewis</hi> being in his <hi>barne,</hi> diſcerned on to run
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:30840:22"/>apace by him: he looked out to ſee who it was, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived it was <hi>Enoch: Iohn</hi> haſted after him to overtake him, but could not obtaine ſight of him any more. Thereupon <hi>Iohn</hi> ſent one of the Schollers (being <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nochs</hi> ſiſters ſonne) after him to his fathers houſe, who brought <hi>Iohn Lewis</hi> word that he was at his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers houſe. As <hi>Enoch</hi> went home hee met with Maſter <hi>Ieremy Powell,</hi> to whom <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noch</hi> ſaid, get your Armour, and prepare your ſelfe, for yonder is the Scrivener at <hi>Biſhops Castle</hi> will bring the Enemies upon us, and though <hi>Enoch</hi> would not at firſt be perſwaded to goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more to the Scrivener to learne to write, yet about
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:30840:22"/>a fortnight after he came to him and beſtowed drinke upon him, and payed him what hee had promiſed for teaching him to write, <hi>viz.</hi> five Shillings, thanking him, and ſaid hee was ſorry for the words he had ſpoken of him. This is it, and in this manner, that the foreſaid <hi>William Tanner</hi> tould the Author of the <hi>Looking-glaſſe</hi> concerning <hi>Enoch,</hi> and all thoſe whom I have na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, will juſtifie the truth hereof, who are none of them Puritans.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>Sect. 6.</head>
               <p>As for the ſecond argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the <hi>Looking-glaſse,</hi> which the Author page one
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:30840:23"/>hundred ſaith was likewiſe told him by <hi>William Tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,</hi> to prove <hi>Enoch</hi> to bee Lunaticke, touching the ſhrill voyce which he heard in the Church of <hi>Clunne,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Enoch</hi> prepare page one hundred foure, the ſaid <hi>William Tanner</hi> utterly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyeth the telling of any ſuch thing unto him: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can I learne of any bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy that there was any ſuch thing: and if <hi>Enoch</hi> had had any ſuch conceit, it were a further argument of his Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacy. Let therefore the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of that Invention take heed leaſt the Lying Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit hold not as much inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, and take as ſtrong poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of his ſoule, as he did of <hi>Enochs,</hi> according to <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nochs</hi> adviſe page one hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:30840:23"/>and five, for from the time that hee went ſo into the river as aforeſaid, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of his diſtraction en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed. The ſaid <hi>William Tanner</hi> likewiſe denyeth that he ever tould the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the <hi>Looking-glaſſe</hi> of the third argument, men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned page one hundred and ſeven, concerning the uſe of Purging and Phlebo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomie, to mitigate the ſtrength of humours, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing malady and diſtemper in his mind, though it bee true as before is ſet forth, that once he was let bloud by the Barbour Chirurgion of <hi>Diſhops Caſtle.</hi> But there was never any trayning of the band of Captaine <hi>Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</hi> at <hi>Newport</hi> as there is alledged, as the ſaid Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:30840:24"/>aſſureth me: who likewiſe denyeth that hee tould the Author of the <hi>Looking-glaſſe</hi> that he never heard of any diſtemper by Lunacy or frantick moodes in <hi>Enoch</hi> his Souldier, as is alledged page 111. for I my ſelfe-ſhewing that paſſage in Maſter <hi>Studlyes</hi> booke to the ſame Maſter <hi>Scriven,</hi> who is of no leſſe worth then hee is acknowledged in the ſame booke to be, he preſently brought one of his Souldiers to me, who had excuſed <hi>Enochs</hi> abſence from a training in regard of a fit of diſtraction then up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, and this Souldier by name <hi>Eraſmus Iones</hi> was familiarly acquainted with <hi>Enoch,</hi> and a neare neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to him. It was growne
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:30840:24"/>a generall report upon the grounds before ſet downe, that <hi>Enoch</hi> was diſtracted: yea it was a common terme about <hi>Biſhops Caſtle,</hi> and it paſſed for current and cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible in all the Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourhood thereabout, that <hi>Enoch</hi> was ſubject to Luna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie and diſtraction; as the Author of the <hi>Looking-glaſſe</hi> ſayeth page 99, and that in a fit of diſtraction hee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted thoſe horrible Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, as his carriage the day and night before the perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tration of them will farther manifeſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <head>Sect. 7.</head>
               <p>For upon thurſday be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the murder commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:30840:25"/>being Market day at <hi>Knighton</hi> in the County of <hi>Radnor, Enoch went</hi> thither againſt the mind of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Mother, and Brother, as himſelfe confeſſed to <hi>Thomas Howels</hi> his kinſman; and being there he told the ſaid <hi>Thomas,</hi> that the occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his then comming thither, was to ſpeake with his Siſter <hi>Margaret,</hi> for he heard that the blacke Oxe was to be in the Towne to be fold that day; which Oxe (ſaid <hi>Enoch</hi> to <hi>Thomas Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wels</hi>) your Father and your Vncle <hi>Henry</hi> know very well. Theſe words of <hi>Enoch</hi> to <hi>Thomas</hi> (knowing that there was no ſuch matter) perſwaded <hi>Thomas Howel</hi> that <hi>Enoch</hi> was then in a fit of diſtraction. <hi>Enoch</hi> like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:30840:25"/>enquired of his kinſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man <hi>Howels</hi> whether he had ſeene <hi>Margaret</hi> the Siſter of Maſter <hi>Richard Iames</hi> in <hi>Knighton</hi> that day? And though <hi>Thomas Howels</hi> could not tell that ſhee was in the Towne, yet <hi>Enoch</hi> had in a ſhort time found her out by enquiry, and called his kinſeman <hi>Howels</hi> to come in with them to drinke, telling him that he meant to marry with her that night, though intruth he was then not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with her: they went in together to drinke with the aforeſaid maide, with whom <hi>Enoch</hi> often whiſpered, ſitting next unto her, and ſpake in Welſh: but ſhee diſliking his moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and weary of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, made haſt to be gone,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:30840:26"/>giving him a flat deny all, yet <hi>Enoch</hi> went out of the houſe with her, but preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly turned backe to <hi>Thomas Howels,</hi> and ſhortly after rode home without any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſpeech with the ſaid maid, notwithſtanding that night following <hi>Enoch</hi> (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in bed with his brother <hi>Iohn</hi>) roſe out of his bed, and went ſuddenly to the town of <hi>Clunne:</hi> his brother <hi>Iohn</hi> alſo aroſe and went with him, and they came thither about midnight, where <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noch</hi> called at the houſe of one <hi>Urſula Iones</hi> and <hi>Eraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus Iones</hi> her ſonne before named roſe up and came to them: <hi>Enoch</hi> asked what company was in the houſe, and whether Maſter <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtopher Powell</hi> a Curate and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:30840:26"/>the aforeſaid <hi>Margaret Iames</hi> were there? <hi>Eraſmus</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered they were not there. No ſaid <hi>Enoch?</hi> Then ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they have miſtaken me, or I them: though in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truth there was no appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of meeting betweene them. But <hi>Enochs</hi> brother <hi>Iohn</hi> privately wiſhed <hi>Eraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus Iones</hi> to perſwade <hi>Enoch</hi> to goe home, and tould him he was out of his ſences, which alſo the ſaid <hi>Eraſmus</hi> had diſcovered, being <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nochs</hi> friend and fellow Souldier as aforeſaid, and therefore he did perſwade <hi>Enoch</hi> to goe home with his Brother <hi>Iohn,</hi> and they did ſo. <hi>Iohn</hi> in the morning ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted old <hi>Edward ap E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>van</hi> their father with what had happened, and deſired
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:30840:27"/>his father to ſeeke for ſome helpe for his brother, and after went to plough, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <hi>Enoch</hi> at home, who fetcht in his fathers horſe, whereupon the old Man rode to <hi>Biſhops Caſtle</hi> upon the Friday being market day there, and ſpake to Barbour Chirurgion afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named to come to let his Sonne <hi>Enoch</hi> bloud, as he had once formerly done. But when the old man came home, he found his wife and ſonne <hi>Iohn</hi> the ſame day both ſlaine in the houſe in ſeverall roomes, their heads being cut off and carried thence: but hee found not his ſonne <hi>Enoch,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore imagined that he had committed that cruell Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. And here it is remar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kable,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:30840:27"/>that in that place where he did uſually read the word of God and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, he was tempted, over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, and committed this fearefull ſinne. It is thought and was confeſſed, that <hi>Iohn</hi> was ſleeping when hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived his deaths wound, though it were not his cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome after his wearineſſe with labour to repoſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in ſlumber for an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer on the end of a table boord, upon a cuſhion, as the Author of the <hi>Looking<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glaſſe</hi> ſaith page 38. for his watching &amp; traveling with <hi>Enoch</hi> to <hi>Clunne</hi> as is before expreſſed, was the cauſe of his heavy ſleepe after he came from plough.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:30840:28"/>
               <head>Sect. 8.</head>
               <p>Now I referre it to the impartiall reader, whether theſe things before ſetdown (though many other alſo might be added) be not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient arguments of <hi>Enochs</hi> diſtraction. And if onely the <hi>Puritans</hi> about <hi>Biſhops Caſtle</hi> conceaved ſo, then is the country indeed full of <hi>Puritans,</hi> for not onely they who conducted him to the Gaole, but generally all were of that opinion, yet the Author of the <hi>Looking-glaſſe</hi> is ſo mad as to take <hi>Enochs</hi> owne word that hee was not mad, as appeareth page 99. and thereby con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaveth, that he giveth <hi>non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformiſts</hi>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:30840:28"/>a deepe diſguſt in the relation and (as he conceaveth) evident refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the arguments con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincing <hi>Enochs</hi> Lunacy, by his denyall of it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <head>Sect. 9.</head>
               <p>After this murder com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by <hi>Enoch,</hi> and after he had hidden the heads of his Mother and Brother; he himſelfe went to <hi>Guilden Downe</hi> to the houſe of <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger Howels,</hi> Father of <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Howels</hi> before menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned: and thither the ſame day ſhortly after came the Hue and cry, upon which <hi>Enoch</hi> was apprehended, and brought before Sir <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Howard,</hi> and there hee
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:30840:29"/>confeſſed to the foreſaid Maſter <hi>Powell</hi> Vicar of <hi>Clunne,</hi> where he had hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den the heads, and there they were found: but he himſelfe (having likewiſe confeſſed the murder) as by his examination upon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord appeareth (was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducted to the Gaole at <hi>Shrewsbury,</hi> not by the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable of the Hundred, as is by Maſter <hi>Studley</hi> related p. 48. but by the Sergeants of <hi>Clunne</hi> and others: neither were they to paſſe by <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nochs</hi> Fathers houſe, nor did he turne into the houſe (for it was out of their way) nor made that reply to his ſiſter, wee live in a falſe Church, as ſhee her ſelfe affirmeth, nor did her husband relate ſuch words to Maſter <hi>Stud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley,</hi>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:30840:29"/>or offer to affirme them upon his oath in any Court of this Kingdom, as is falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly related page 50. for he ſaieth he will affirme upon his oath, that he did not ſay ſo in the preſence of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Studley,</hi> or any where elſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
               <head>Sect. 10.</head>
               <p>In the way to <hi>Shrewsbury</hi> Gaole, they take up their lodging at <hi>Powderbacke,</hi> and there wee read of ſtrange things that happened, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth in the <hi>Looking-glaſſe</hi> pag. 51, 52, 53, 54, 55, and 56 as that <hi>Enoch</hi> ſtared with indignation upon the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable of the Hundred, that he ſtarted up in a deſperate
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:30840:30"/>rage, and catcht at a Spit to have goared the Conſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and that a moſt feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full noyſe is heard in the Street neere the dore of the houſe where <hi>Enoch</hi> lay, as if it had beene the ratling of the wheeles of two or three Cartes furiouſly dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, this noyſe wakened <hi>Enoch,</hi> affrighted him <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So many particulars rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, ſo many falſehoods, for there was no Conſtable there to be goared: there was indeed the Sergeants of <hi>Clunne</hi> as I ſaid before, he hath aſſured me that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there, nor in all the way, did <hi>Enoch</hi> offer any violence to him, or any in the company, neither did he catch at any Spit, onely he looked earneſtly and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:30840:30"/>gaſtly upon every object, like a diſtracted man, as he and the reſt conceived him to be, as I ſaid before. And as touching the noyſe in the ſtreet, one of the watchmen tould me, that they ſaw ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parently the cauſe of the noyſe, which was the run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of Calves along the ſtreet, by the doore of the houſe where <hi>Enoch</hi> was lodged, neither did he come downe naked, or uſe that exclamation: all which if true, had been no arguments of <hi>Puritaniſme.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
               <head>Sect. 11.</head>
               <p>And now <hi>Enoch</hi> is brought to the Gaole at <hi>Shrewsbury,</hi> and he with his <hi>Mittimus</hi>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:30840:31"/>delivered to the Goaler. Many deſire to ſee and to queſtion this notorious ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefactor, he never that I can heare off, denyed the fact to any; but the cauſe inducing him thereunto is earneſtly enquired after alſo. <hi>Fælix qui potuit rerum cognoſcere cauſas,</hi> ſayeth the Poet. What the opinion of the Neighbourhood was, is formerly declared: they that knew the courſe of his life, and obſerved the duti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full reſpect of <hi>Enoch</hi> to his Father and Mother, and the love and affection between his brother and him, could imagine no reaſon or cauſe of thoſe hainous facts, but Sathans working upon his diſtraction and Lunacy. For it was generally obſerved,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:30840:31"/>that they lovingly agreed together (as is ſet forth in the <hi>Looking-glaſſe</hi> page 32) from their infant yeares and weaning from the breaſt of their mother to the one and thirtieth yeare of the age of the younger of them (which was the yeare wherein <hi>Iohn</hi> was ſlaine) during which time <hi>Enoch</hi> aſſured Maſter <hi>Studly,</hi> engaging his truth and ſalvation upon it, there had never fallen outanyver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ball quarrel, no not ſo much as the Tearme (thou) had ever paſſed in anger from the one to the other. Yet how ſoon after <hi>Enochs</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to <hi>Shrewſbury</hi> Goale are other cauſes vented, if not there invented? And thoſe gathered alſo from <hi>Enochs</hi> confeſſion, as the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:30840:32"/>profeſſion of love was. And the cauſes are ſeverall and diſagreeing betweene themſelves. Now if the confeſſion of <hi>Enoch</hi> had beene certaine and conſtant to all, the cauſe had beene more evident: but it was not, at the leaſt the relation of it, ſheweth it not to be ſo: for one while <hi>Enoch</hi> aſſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth one cauſe, another time the contrary, a third time he differs in aſſigning one and the ſame cauſe. Firſt, hee gives this to bee the cauſe, to draw the children of light out of darkneſſe, and to declare his owne zeale to the word of God pag. 35. when he gave this reaſon, hewaseither <hi>non com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos mentis,</hi> or he conceived his mother and his brother
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:30840:32"/>to be children of light; he intended to doe them a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit to deliver them out of darkneſſe by taking away their lives; and this could not proceed from hatred, but love: what then is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of the rage, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, ſo often repeated and agravated by the Author of the <hi>Looking-glaſſe?</hi> Now this was done as is before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, to declare his zeale to the word of God, yet at another time, he confeſſeth that he fell into thoſe facts by ſinne, as page 81. Sinne and zeale to Gods word are not the ſame. Againe he makes difference in opinion touching kneeling to be the one cauſe pag. 31.72.127. for we muſt underſtand that after <hi>Enoch</hi> came to <hi>Shrews<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury</hi>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:30840:33"/>Goale, he is there diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered to be a Puritan, nay a downe-right Separatiſt; yet (as before is ſaid) he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſeparated himſelfe from his owne pariſh Church, within which Pariſh, or within which hundred there was never Puritan known to be ſo farre as I can un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand. And it is confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed that <hi>Enoch</hi> read Prayers out of the Service Booke of our <hi>Engliſh Church,</hi> in his fathers houſe, in a conſtant courſe pag. 22. this is no ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of a <hi>Separatiſt</hi> or a Puritan. He conſtantly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaved the Holy Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion in his owne pariſh Church, and that reverent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly uſing the poſture of knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, as is teſtified by the foreſaid Vicar of <hi>Clunne</hi> and
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:30840:33"/>the pariſhioners, except it were at <hi>Easter</hi> next before the committing of theſe murders, and yet then being required, he bowed his knee as is before ſaid; ſo that in his practiſe he was confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable.
<note place="margin">pag. 72.</note> But ſaith Maſter <hi>Studley</hi> upon <hi>Enochs</hi> confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, he differed in opinion from his mother and bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, touching the geſture at the Communion, they would kneele, and he would ſit and bow his body, and for this cauſe onely his wrath kindled againſt his brother, and in that wrath he ſlew him, and yet page 123. he yeelded not that he ſlew his brother onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of his kneeling. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Enochs</hi> confeſſion is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine, contrary and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictory.
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:30840:34"/>I confeſſe to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie my ſelfe fully in this point, I have ſpoken with, and ſeene teſtified under the hands of divers both of the Clergy and Laity, men in all points conformable, that both going to the Goale, and whiles he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained there, he utterly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed, that the difference in opinion betweene his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and him, was any cauſe at all why he ſlew him: and that the ſtrong temptation of ſinne was the only cauſe. The perſons who teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie this, are Maſter <hi>Powell</hi> aforenamed Maſter <hi>Smith,</hi> Maſter <hi>Needham,</hi> Maſter <hi>Bourne,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Maſter <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas Matthews.</hi>
                  </note> Maſter <hi>Bedford,</hi> al of the Cleargie, beſides many more of the Cleargie and Laity: yea ſome, that have
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:30840:34"/>beene preſent with Maſter <hi>Studley</hi> in the Gaole, have aſſured me, that to Maſter <hi>Studly</hi> himſelfe he utterly denyed that the difference about kneeling was any cauſe at all, but that Sinwas the cauſe moving him to commit thoſe murders, and ſo it is ſet downe by Maſter <hi>Studley</hi> in the <hi>Looking-glaſſe</hi> pag. 81.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
               <head>Sect. 12.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Enochs</hi> reaſon for bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and not kneeling, rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Maſter <hi>Studly</hi> in his owne phraſe (for whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver knew <hi>Enoch</hi> wil be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident it was never his) will better ſatisfie the reader, that he was no Puritan; and
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:30840:35"/>it is this pag. 16. For in the ſite and geſture of kneeling the leggs are caſt behind the reſt of the body, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive not that influence of nouriſhment ſpirituall, at leaſt in proportion and meaſure of attraction as the reſt of the body doth, and therefore the geſtures that this vaine, light, and ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced man concepted to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe as moſt convenient in that Sacred act of Gods worſhip were either ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and bowing, or ſitting and bowing of the body. As this geſture of bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is ſingular in <hi>En<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ch,</hi> ſo is the reaſon different from any Puritan or <hi>Non-confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt</hi> that ever I heard or read of. They like not the geſture of kneeling, coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:30840:35"/>it ſuperſtitius, in regard it is a geſture of adoration, and therein nouriſheth thoſe that are popiſhly affected in their opinion of tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation. Now Maſter <hi>Studley</hi> by a diſtinction of his, maketh bowing onely to be a geſture of adorati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for theſe are his words pag. 18. For the poſtures of ſtanding, of ſitting, of knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, being all naturall and bodily actions; without the addition of bowing, which is a mentall and ſpirituall action, and hath relation to ſome other nature, either in the Creator, or in the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to whom it is directed, are in themſelves, as they are actions bodily and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall, neither good nor e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill at all: and doe onely
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:30840:36"/>partake of goodneſſe, or ill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, as the motion of bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with intention of ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration is added unto them. So that by this diſtinction <hi>Enoch</hi> framed a geſture of adoration by his bowing, which Puritans and <hi>Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformiſts</hi> diſtaſte, and ſo he differed from them. But he that well examineth <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nochs</hi> reaſon, and Maſter <hi>Studleys</hi> diſtinction, wil find apparantly, they come out of one forge, and indeed they are alike ſenſeleſſe. And I ſhould have thought Maſter <hi>Studley</hi> had derided <hi>Enochs</hi> reaſon, and had ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken ironically, where he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth it a conceipt ſo ſubli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate, fine, and ſubtill, had he not compared that vaine and franticke reaſon to
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:30840:36"/>the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> devices, and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> the depths of Sathan, therein groſly abuſing thoſe places of Scripture. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.11. and <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.24. for thoſe deviſes and depths of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than</hi> there ſpoken of are not ſuch as may bee diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, avoyded, and derided by the ſhalloweſt judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: but ſuch as from which good Lord deliver us.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="section">
               <head>Sect. 13.</head>
               <p>Other points of Purita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſme are laid to the charge of <hi>Enoch,</hi> by Maſter <hi>Studle</hi> pag. 25. as that he diſliked the Superiority of <hi>Biſhops</hi> the ſigne of the Croſſe i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Baptiſme, and ſuch like:
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:30840:37"/>but none of theſe are inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted upon: onely the diſlike of the geſture of kneeling in the Sacred Communion, is it that makes him a Puritan, yea a Separatiſt,
<note place="margin">page 72.</note> and for this cauſe he ſlew his Brother. And though <hi>Enoch</hi> vary in his confeſſion of the cauſe, though he deny that to be any cauſe, though ſome times he ſay it is not the onely cauſe, and though he aſſigne another cauſe, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hath beene ſhewed, yet Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Studly</hi> by two argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments will prove, that one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for kneeling at the Sacred Communion <hi>Enoch</hi> killed his Mother and Brother The firſt argument is taken out of 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.12.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Looking-glaſſe</hi> pag. 124</note> where the text is, not as <hi>Caine</hi> wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> was of that wicked one
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:30840:37"/>and ſlew his Brother: and wherefore ſlew he him? be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe his own workes were evill, and his Brothers righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous. Here ſaith Maſter <hi>Studley</hi> the conjunction <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is cauſall, as the Learned know, and referre us to the ſole and total cauſe, and not in part aſſignes the cauſe, why <hi>Caine</hi> ſlew his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Therefore <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe I want Logicke, and therefore deſired this work might have beene perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by one more able; yet I want not ſo much rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon as to ſee the weakneſſe of this argument, the cauſe of <hi>Caines</hi> murder is plaine ſo is not <hi>Enochs:</hi> for that, we have the word of <hi>God</hi> expreſly aſſigning the cauſe, which was this, becauſe his
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:30840:38"/>owne workes were evill, and his Brothers righteous: for this, we have onely the confeſſion of a ſinfull wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched man: which confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is uncertaine, variable, and contradictory: ſo that to make this argument hold, Maſter <hi>Studley,</hi> muſt imply that <hi>Enochs</hi> confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (apparantly variable) is as true as Scripture. I ſay no more, I leave it to the Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to Iudge.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="section">
               <head>Sect. 14.</head>
               <p>The ſecond argument is pag. 127. <hi>Enoch ap Eva<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> ſlaies his Brother either for this cauſe onely, that <hi>Iohn</hi> would kneele at the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, or for ſome other
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:30840:38"/>cauſe. But for other cauſe or cauſes, he never pleaded any for himſelfe, but totally excluded all other cauſes. Therefore <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I anſwer, <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noch</hi> pleaded other cauſes, many times to many per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, yea even to Maſter <hi>Studley</hi> himſelfe (as is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore expreſſed) and did ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly deny this to bee any cauſe at al: and therefore this Syllogiſme ſo much brag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged of by the Author, that the thing affirmed remaines pregnant, dilucidate, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincible, is not binding, but directly falſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="section">
               <head>Sect. 15.</head>
               <p>I ſhould not have inſiſted ſo much upon the clearing
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:30840:39"/>of this wretched <hi>Enoch</hi> from being a Puritan or non-conformiſt (for I know he was worſe, he was a cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell murderer of his mother and Brother) nor upon the cauſe moving him to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit that hainous crime, (for I thinke and beleeve that a non-conformiſt may be a Subject upon which the Devill might worke, ſince even the wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>thy ſervants of God have grievouſly fallen, as <hi>Noah, David, Lot, Peter,</hi> and others recorded in holy Scripture) had not the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the <hi>Looking-glaſſe</hi> uncharitably charged his ſeducement, and inveigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into the opinions of non-conformitie upon ſome Miniſters or lay perſons, and this he is ſo confident
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:30840:39"/>of, that he knoweth it to be ſo, as ſurely as he knoweth it to be true that his owne ſoule is living within him, as is expreſſed pag. 137, 138 139, moreat large. For ful ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction in this point, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire the reader to obſerve; firſt, that the ſaid Author layeth his former grounds upon <hi>Enochs</hi> confeſſion in his conference with him in the Goale: this upon his owne conjecture, diſcredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>Enochs</hi> flat denyall of it, for ſo Maſter <hi>Studley</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe informeth us pag. 138. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> he anſ wered him as he had done often before, and continued in that obſtinacy to his death, that not from man, but from God he had receaved thoſe conceipts: and being particularly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:30840:40"/>how he came firſt to diſlike the geſtures of his betters for wiſedome <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">pag 75, 76.</note> as is largely ſet down whether by conference with any Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters diſaffected to peace and unity? or by private per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion of ſome of his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance? Or by exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of any? Or by reading of Schiſmaticall bookes? <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noch</hi> anſwered, by none of all theſe meanes, but by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of Gods word. Doth this defamation of his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren in the Miniſters and others, agree with the rules of charity? or doth it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from a gracious incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to ſolid Piety, and a publicke declaration of an honeſt heart, diſpoſed to peace and unity?
<note place="margin">pag. 96:</note> this Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Studley</hi> bragges of but
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:30840:40"/>practiſeth not. Secondly, though he boaſteth himſelfe to be the known <hi>Antipuritan</hi> of the county, as is ſaid, and ſo moſt likely to know the <hi>puritans</hi> in the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ty, yet he namethnone that ſeduced <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noch,</hi> he teleth us of <hi>puritans</hi> about <hi>Biſhops Castle,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">pag. 99.</note> that fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medarguments to make <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noch</hi> appeare to be lunatick, and thereby perhaps inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mateth that by ſome there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abouts <hi>Enoch</hi> was ſeduced; for it is before confeſſed that <hi>Enoch</hi> all his life time had his abode within two or three Miles of <hi>Biſhops Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle.</hi> I my ſelfe have dwelt within two miles of the ſaid Towne this forty yeares (for the moſt part) I know moſt of the Cleargy with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Deanery of <hi>Clunne,</hi>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:30840:41"/>in the Dioceſſe of <hi>Hereford,</hi> and I am confident there is not amongſt them all one non-conformiſt, neither is there any of any note (that I can learne) of the laity but doe conforme, and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly in that point of knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in the receaving of the bleſſed Sacrament. Maſter <hi>Studley</hi> ſhould doe well, to make the Puritans known, that they may be reformed, and not conceale them, and yet caſt an aſperſion upon the Eccleſiaſticall and civill government, and that meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon his owne imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, what may the reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Father our preſent Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oceſan, thinke of us in this part of his Dioceſſes? what will the world (to whom we are unknowne other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:30840:41"/>then by report, which falleth out with ſuch preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice in this particular by the <hi>Looking-glaſſe of Schiſme</hi>) conceave of us better, then ſuch a neſt of Puritans and <hi>Non-conformiſts,</hi> as <hi>England</hi> affordeth not the like?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="section">
               <head>Sect. 16.</head>
               <p>Our lately deceaſed Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oceſan, the reverend father in God <hi>Biſhop Lindſel,</hi> much deſired to underſtand that part of his Dioceſſe, tooke ſpeciall notice of every par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular miniſter that were Preachers at the monethly Lecture in <hi>Biſhops Caſtle,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore eſtabliſhed by the <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop</hi> of the ſame Dioceſſe, and by his owne appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:30840:42"/>ſupplied the places of ſome that were lately dead, and they are twelve in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber; all of them in the ſame Deanery of knowne conformity: more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly hee requeſted to be informed about this <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noch ap Evan,</hi> and to ſpeake with his father, and for him I prepared my firſt papers, by whoſe meanes we had very good hopes to have our neighbourhood cleared from the aſperſions laid up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it by the <hi>Looking-glaſſe of Schiſme:</hi> which booke he had read, and therupon (un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till he was enformed to the contrary) conceaved that theſe parts had need of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, for until he ſpake with ſome that could en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme him in the particulars
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:30840:42"/>concerning <hi>Enoch,</hi> he did not imagine the relation to have beene ſo falſe in the chiefe points: but it pleaſed GOD to take him out of this life, before what wee wiſhed came to paſſe. The ſame reverend father deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering his opinion concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the ſaid booke (which would not have pleaſed Maſter <hi>Studley</hi>) asked a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of this Countrey whether he had not obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved a paſſage in it concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Maſter <hi>Studlies</hi> great and ungodly wit, adding that he that ſaid ſo of him, did him wrong, he would excuſe him of the firſt of thoſe, if any could free him from the latter: of which he can by no meanes be excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, ſince he hath put his
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:30840:43"/>pen on worke to publiſh ſuch ſcandalous ſlanders a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Cleargie and lay perſons as affected to non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformity, ſeducing <hi>Enoch</hi> into his opinions, and to conceale both their names and the true cauſe of the fact.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="section">
               <head>Sect. 17.</head>
               <p>We ſee what worke Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Studley</hi> hath made us in the Gaole at <hi>Shrewsbury,</hi> now the Gaole delivery draweth neare, and the Iudges are in their Circuit at the next County of <hi>Staf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> adjoyning to <hi>Shropſhire;</hi> there they are informed of this murtherer by the reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>end father the <hi>Biſhop</hi> of
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:30840:43"/>
                  <hi>Lichfield</hi> and <hi>Coventry,</hi> who was ſo carefull not to miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>report, as that he required Maſter <hi>Studley,</hi> who was his informer, to lay downe in writing under his owne hand, and ſubſcription of his name the truth of the particulars receaved from the priſoner, as Maſter <hi>Studley</hi> confeſſeth pag. 121. The reverend judges who ever laboured to ſuppreſſe <hi>Schiſme</hi> and non-conformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, being at <hi>Shrewsbury</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended the Iuſtices of Peace, that had not enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med them of ſo notorious a malefactor, before they came to heare of it in a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon; when as in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uth the Iuſtices themſelves that dwelt neareſt to the place, where the offence was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:30840:44"/>were Ignorant, that the offence was committed upon any ſuch ground or reaſon as non-conformity. But at the aſſiſes, <hi>Enoch</hi> is ſeverally indited for the murders by him commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted upon his mother and brother, upon the ſeverall indictments he is ſeverally araigned, upon his araign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments he pleadeth guilty, upon which plea, as you ſhall heare anon, hee had judgement (to be executed) given upon him, according to juſtice and regular pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding: though Maſter <hi>Studley</hi> (aſſuring us in the word of a miniſter, that we have a relation of ſuch ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiall truth, as he will maintaine againſt any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon living upon the face of
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:30840:44"/>the earth) be not aſhamed on heareſay to deliver, as he hath ſet it down;
<note place="margin">pag. 135, 136.</note> that the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of his murders, ſo ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> publiſhed to the world, by his free and voluntary confeſſion, might have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented the formal proces of law, by jury, conviction, and caſting, and have put him into the power of the judge for ſentence of death from his owne acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and expreſſion of his guilt: but for more ſtrength of juſtice, and regularity of proceeding, the jury found him guilty, and made him lyable to ſentence of death. As if after <hi>Enoch</hi> had plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded guilty, it had been more for the ſtrength of Iuſtice and regularity of procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to have tryed him by a
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:30840:45"/>jury of life and death. The Iudges (for both of them ſate at his araignment) were carefull to find out the cauſe moving <hi>Enoch</hi> to this bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous murder, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore after he had pleaded guilty, one of the judges asked him, what the cauſe might be, moving him to kill his mother and his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, whether there were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny difference or falling out betweene them? <hi>Enoch</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered there was ſome dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference in reaſoning be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene his brother and him about the geſture of knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling at the Communion. It was then urged by the judg, that then that was the cauſe why he ſlew his brother? <hi>Enoch</hi> anſwered no, it was not, being againe demanded
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:30840:45"/>what then might be the cauſe? He anſwered, the ſtrong temptation of ſinne. He was further asked whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he did not deſire to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the holy Communion before his execution? He anſwered, yes he did. It be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then declared unto him by Baron <hi>Trevor,</hi> that he might uſe no other geſture in that action, but that which was preſcribed by law, and practiſed by the Church, which was knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and that no Miniſter ſhould deliver it him other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe: and it being ſo, he was demanded what in that caſe he would doe? <hi>Enoch</hi> anſwered, hee had rather bow his body; yet rather then he ſhould not receive the Communion, he would
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:30840:46"/>kneele. This paſſed openly at his araignment upon fry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day the Sixteenth of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt.</hi> The judgement to be given upon <hi>Enoch</hi> was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred untill the next day being Saterday, upon which day and before judgement <hi>Enoch</hi> is brought to the Iudges Chamber, and there privately they both exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine him touching the cauſe moving him to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the murder, but as I heard from one of the Iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, he w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> no other cauſe, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hen what he had done publickely. Afterwards being brought to the barre (without a jury to finde him guilty) he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived his judgement from Sir <hi>William Iones,</hi> the Iudge that for that time ſate up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:30840:46"/>Life and Death.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="section">
               <head>Sect. 18.</head>
               <p>The <hi>Sheriffe</hi> being com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to ſee execution done, was directed, that he ſhould be hanged in chains, in ſome convenient and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent place not very far from the place where the murder was committed; and therupon he is brought to <hi>Biſhops Castle,</hi> where Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Gervaſe Needham</hi> is Vicar, the learned Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man and miniſter of that pariſh, mentioned by Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Studley</hi> pag. 161. He repaireth to <hi>Enoch</hi> (as he was informed) by the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment of the Iudges, and conferreth with him,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:30840:47"/>to the end the better to prepare him for death, then ſhortly to enſue, for it was the day of his execution, and this was in the preſence of divers of the Cleargy and laity: which confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and the paſſages ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in before, and at his death, the ſaid Maſter <hi>Needham</hi> preſently after committed to writing, and hereafter it followeth, as it was by him delivered to me, without change or alteration.</p>
               <p>It being asked, whether he was truly and unfained<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſorry for the fact where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he ſtood condemned?</p>
               <p>He anſwered that hee was ſo, that he thought in his heart no man living had ſuch a weight of ſinne upon him, or had ever done the
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:30840:47"/>like hainous murder, that he was Iuſtly condemned and willing to dye for it, that he was truly ſenſible of the ſinne committed, and heartily ſorry that he could not be more ſorry for it: yet that he did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidently believe God would have mercy upon his ſoule, deſiring all to pray for him.</p>
               <p>Whether he did not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive ſome diſparagement, or diſgrace, or injury, from his brother and mother? and whether he did not conceive them to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane and wicked people, unworthy to live? And whether he did not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive his father or himſelfe to be of a more undefiled &amp; unſpotted converſation?</p>
               <p>He anſwered that hee
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:30840:48"/>thought them all to be reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious and godly, and (with a great ſigh) that his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was ever loving and deare to him, no man had a better brother then he had of him, and that there was no malice nor difference betwixt them at the time he ſlew them, onely ſome two dayes before they had diſcourſed of ſtanding and kneeling at the Sacrament, himſelfe approving of ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding or bowing rather, but there was no high words, or anger, or diſcontentment betweene them upon that conference.</p>
               <p>What might bee the grounds of his opinion for ſtanding and bowing at the Sacrament?</p>
               <p>Hee anſwered that hee
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:30840:48"/>conceived it to be our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours geſture at the firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution: and further that it is written, <hi>Behold I stand at the dore and knocke.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whether hee did not thinke it Idolatry to kneele at the Sacrament? And whether he did not ground his action upon that in <hi>Deu.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 6, 7, 8, 9, and 10. where it i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> written, if thy brother the ſonne of thy mother entice thee ſaying, <hi>Let us go ſerve other Gods</hi> &amp;c. thou ſhalt not conſent unto him <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but thou ſhalt ſurely kill him, thine hand ſhall be firſt upon him <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He heard ſuch things and many untruths had beene reported of him, but for his part he thought it no Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try to kneele at the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:30840:49"/>neither did he ground that action upon any ſuch text of holy Scripture, and therein hee had manifeſt wrong.</p>
               <p>Whether he did not fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent any private meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and conventicles in the Neighbourhood or elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where? Or whether he did not ground that fact upon ſome doctrine or words he had heard at Sermons o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Lectures at <hi>Biſhops Caſtle</hi> or elſewhere? Or ſome pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate diſcourſe with any of the miniſtry or other of his acquaintance?</p>
               <p>He anſwered that he was never at any ſuch meeting or conventicle, neither did he in any private diſcourſe, or from any preacher heare or receive any doctrine o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:30840:49"/>counſell that might encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage or move him to ſuch a fact.</p>
               <p>What then might be the cauſe, if none of theſe? Or what end he propoſed to himſelfe in the action?</p>
               <p>He anſwered that it was the temptation of ſinne. But being deſired to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine himſelfe in thoſe tearmes, he ſaid it was the corruption of the fleſh and <hi>Sathans</hi> ſuggeſtion.</p>
               <p>It being urged that our ſubtile adverſary the eaſie, to worke upon us, is wont to propoſe in every temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation ſome matter either of profit or pleaſure, and ſometimes even the glory of God, (as the end) there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the rather to deceive us and leade us into ſinne?</p>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:30840:50"/>
               <p>He anſwered that hee could give no reaſon or ground at all why he did the act, neither did he think what might be the end or iſſue of it being done, and that he never thought of ſuch a fact, towards man, woman, or child, till within one houre or leſſe before the murder was done, and that his thoughts did ſo riſe upon him that he could not have any reſt or quiet till he had done the deed.</p>
               <p>Whether he intended to have murthered them both when he firſt laid hands on his brother?</p>
               <p>He anſwered, no ſurely; but his mother came in to reſcue his brother, not yet fully dead, and ſo wounded her alſo mortally, and a
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:30840:50"/>length cut off both their heads, not deliberating with himſelfe upon it.</p>
               <p>Whether the Devill did not then appeare to him, and (as ſome reported) give the Axe into his hand vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently enforcing him unto the fact?</p>
               <p>He anſwered, no, there was no ſuch matter, the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill did not then, or at any other time appeare unto him.</p>
               <p>Whether hee did not ſometimes ſee a viſion of the holy Ghoſt appearing to him in the likeneſſe of a Dove, as was reported?</p>
               <p>He anſwered that indeed he did conceive a thing in the likeneſſe of a Dove full of brightneſſe to come into the Chamber in his fathers
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:30840:51"/>houſe, where he then lay upon his bed in the night broad awake, and that he thought it to be the holy Ghoſt.</p>
               <p>It being urged, that the ſpirit of God would not ſurely have appeared but to ſome ſpeciall end in ſuch an extraordinary manner, and queſtion being made whether hee felt himſelfe thereby illuminated further in the myſteries of ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? Or in the ſence of his owne ſinnes more hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled? Or whether it impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed any particular charge or command upon him? Or revealed any ſecret of note unto him at the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent?</p>
               <p>He anſwered that he was not ſenſible of any ſuch o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perations
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:30840:51"/>as theſe or the like: in ſo much that after further diſcourſe in this particular, he ſaid that he knew not what to thinke of it: it might be the diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered worke of his braine for ought he knew to the contrary.</p>
               <p>Whether he did not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire a kinſman to convey him ſecretly to <hi>Biſhops Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle</hi> to the miniſter or Vicar there? for he had an intent to ſacrifice one head which he had privately hidden to him: and the other to a neighbouring Gentleman as was reported?</p>
               <p>He anſwered that he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver made mention of any ſuch word as head or ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice: onely he had a deſire to ſee that Gentleman, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:30840:52"/>to reveale unto him what he had done: and to aske advice from him what he were beſt to do (his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience then grievouſly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſing him of the murder he had committed) as well for the ſatisfaction of the Law, which he deſired, as for the ſafety of his ſoule being then in himſelfe help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, and even deſpairing of mercy.</p>
               <p>Whether he was former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly well acquainted with the ſaid Vicar of <hi>Biſhops Caſtle,</hi> and how long he had been ſo?</p>
               <p>Hee anſwered that hee knew him well by ſight, but never had any confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence or acquaintance with him, onely hee had heard him ſometimes preach: and
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:30840:52"/>once paſſing by the church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, the ſaid Vicar asked him his name, and how far he travelled that way.</p>
               <p>What moved him ſo far (being a meere ſtranger) to mention the ſaid Vicar of <hi>Biſhops Caſtle,</hi> and upon examination to ſhew him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe more willing to open himſelfe to the ſaid Vicar, then to any other? And to receive the Sacrament ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from him, and upon his firſt motion (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding his former opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) willingly to receive the holy Sacrament kneeling?</p>
               <p>He anſwered that often he had ſeen him, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times heard him preach Gods word though ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: and he thought him a good man, and had heard
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:30840:53"/>his father very much com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend the ſaid Vicar both for his paines in the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, as alſo for his care in teaching, and love to two of his grandchildren then Scholers under the ſaid Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>car of <hi>Biſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ps Caſtle.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whether he did earneſtly deſire to receive the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Sacrament at that time? and for what end or cauſe did he ſo deſire it?</p>
               <p>He anſwered that hee much deſired it, for hee thought and believed it to be an eſpeciall meanes that GOD had ordained to ſtrengthen his faith in he apprehenſion of Chriſt his merits unto ſalvation. So he received it reverently knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and acknowledged that he received comfort by it.</p>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:30840:53"/>
               <p>It being urged that not onely the bleſſed Martyrs, but even guilty malefactors alſo, dying under the Law juſtly condemned for felo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, murder and the like, many of them at the place of execution, in one hours before their death, by their open and hearty confeſſion, earneſtneſſe of prayer, holy exhortations to the people, by cheerfulneſſe of pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſes and the like, have much glorifyed God?</p>
               <p>He anſwered that he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved ſo to doe, that he would make the beſt uſe of his ſhort time he could, to that purpoſe he deſired a Bible with the ſinging Pſalmes, intending to make choice of the thirtieth Pſalme as moſt proper for
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:30840:54"/>that occaſion, and reflecting upon the preſent condition wherein hee ſtood as hee conceived.</p>
               <p>So paſſing to the place of execution not unwilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, for he ſeemed often to be weary of the throng and preſſe of people, many of the ſame queſtions were againe urged, concerning the fact and circumſtances thereof: to which he brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gave the ſame anſwer as before, onely with this dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference as followeth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the reaſon or cauſe why he ſhould doe it. The queſtion being propoſed thus, did you therefore kill your Mother and your bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther becauſe they received the Sacrament kneeling or no?</p>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:30840:54"/>
               <p>He anſwered that was not only the cauſe; whence it was argued that it was part of the cauſe and that he withall concealed ſome further reaſon alſo that might move him to do the fact.</p>
               <p>Being therefore urged to a further ſatisfactory an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to declare the whole truth, and confeſſe at large, whether that, <hi>vizt.</hi> their kneeling was the cauſe wholly? Or if but in part, whether yet he had not a further reaſon, and what that might be?</p>
               <p>He denyed that it was any part of the cauſe, or that he was able to give any cauſe, or reaſon at al of the fact. In ſo much that a grave and reverend divine anſwered
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:30840:55"/>thereupon in theſe words; then <hi>Enoch</hi> it ſeemes that word might wel have been left out, I meane the word, onely.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="section">
               <head>Sect. 19.</head>
               <p>For further ſatisfaction as touching his manner of death: he made upon the ladder a ſhort, and generall confeſſion, that he was guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of much ſinne, and of this murder in particular, that he was ſenſible of the heynouſneſſe of the fact, and did earneſtly repent him of it: hee exhorted the people by his example, to beware, and watch over themſelves, leaſt they fall into temptation in like ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. After this he read the
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:30840:55"/>thirtieth Pſalme; and he came downe, and kneeling upon the ground he made a generall Prayer, by way of confeſſion of ſinne in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, and petition for pardon and remiſſion, briefly tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching upon this fact of murder therein. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing urged to pray againe for pardon of that ſinne more particularly, he knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led downe the ſecond time, and enlarged himſelfe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that ſinne, and the hai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouſneſſe of murder, and this murder eſpecially, with petition of pardon and forgiveneſſe, to the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction and comfort of thoſe preſent, who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended the prayer, and praiſed God, in hope they had of the ſalvation of the
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:30840:56"/>poore ſoule, After that he read another <hi>Pſal.</hi> upon the Ladder, and ſo ſtill calling upon God, and the people to pray for him, he prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to die with much trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling in his leggs and joints, but with a cheerefull voice he ſpent his laſt breath in <hi>Lord have mercy, God have mercy upon my ſoule.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="section">
               <head>Sect. 20.</head>
               <p>Theſe narrations premi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, ſerve firſt, to manifeſt upon what weake reaſons and falſe grounds Maſter <hi>Studleys</hi> accuſations in theſe particulars are framed. For he (having gayned from <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noch</hi> a confeſſion that there was a difference in reſoning
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:30840:56"/>between his brother and him, touching the geſture of kneeling) concludeth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, that he was a downe right ſeparatiſt: though <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nochs</hi> reaſons alledged may better conclude him to be a mad man then a Puritan. A better reaſon might have beene uſed to have proved him a Puritan, becauſe he was a Proteſtant out of his wits. And he conceiveth he hath given non-confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts a deepe diſguſt in his refutation of the arguments and objections convincing him of Lunacy, by <hi>Enochs</hi> owne deny all that he was mad, as appeareth pag. 99. upon the ſuppoſition that he was a Puritan, he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludeth the cauſe of his murder was puritaniſme
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:30840:57"/>and difference in opinion; and this grounded upon <hi>Enochs</hi> variable and contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictory confeſſion to Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Studley,</hi> as hath beene ſhewed. And hereupon he reſolveth, it muſt needs fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low that he was ſeduced in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to theſe opinions to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of his body and ſoule; therein not crediting <hi>Enochs</hi> often and conſtant denyall thereof. They ſerve alſo to ſhew what manner of man this wretched <hi>Enoch</hi> was conceived to be. By his neighbours, by his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhioners, by the Vicar of the pariſh (who beſt knew him) he was eſteemed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his latter time, a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted or Lunaticke man, though he had his <hi>Lucida intervalla:</hi> but no ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:30840:57"/>no Puritan, or non-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſt: for (as hath beene ſaid) he conſtantly frequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Divine Service in his owne pariſh, and received the Sacraments, even to the time of his falling into this ſinne of murder. And like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to ſhew that Sathan (working upon his predo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minant humour of melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly) tempted him to commit theſe murders: or as he in the Gaole confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to many before named, to the judges at his arraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and at the time of his death, it was the ſtrong temptation of ſinne that moved him to commit them. And that he was not ſeduced into the poynts of Puritaniſme by any of the Clergy or laity, about <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:30840:58"/>Caſtle</hi> or <hi>Clunne</hi> land: for there were none ſuch to perſwade or ſeduce him, as hath been ſhewed. And for more confirmation thereof, I referre it to the better knowledge and teſtimony, of the preſent Chancellor of the Dioceſſe of <hi>Hereford</hi> (Maſter Doctor <hi>Skinner</hi>) who hath continued that place under the three laſt <hi>Biſhops</hi> of that Dioceſſe, and who by preſentments, and other meanes for his infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, is likelieſt to know the ſtate of the country in that behalfe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="section">
               <head>Sect. 21.</head>
               <p>Though in this narrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on we are come to <hi>Enochs</hi>
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:30840:58"/>death, yet death the end of life, giveth not an end to the ſtirres and rumours a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout him: from this Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanicall <hi>Phoenix,</hi> hatcht by Maſter <hi>Studley</hi> in this part of the Country, others have riſen out of the aſhes: for (ſaith he pag. 164.) the dead body of this <hi>Enoch</hi> hanging forth waving in the ayre, more then a fortnight, and leſſe then three weeks, ſome brethren of his owne diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition and faction, who are reſtleſſe in wilfulneſſe (that he ſay not wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe) contrived a device by rearing up a Ladder in the night, a worke of darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, to ſaw off that part of the Gibbet where his body hanged, and tooke it away, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and theſe he tearmeth
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:30840:59"/>ſaucy rebells under the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſard of Puritaniſme.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="section">
               <head>Sect. 22.</head>
               <p>The act of taking downe his body, and that in the night, is not denyed. The queſtion in this alſo wilbe, who, and what manner of perſons the actors were: and theſewere brought to light, before Maſter <hi>Studleys</hi> book came to publik view: and there was great care taken for the diſcovery of ſo great an affront to publik juſtice. For the next day after this act committed, Maſter <hi>Walcot</hi> (a juſtice of peace dwelling neare <hi>Biſhops Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle</hi>) and my ſelfe met there: we fell into conſideration,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:30840:59"/>what meanes was to be u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed to diſcover the offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ers. It was conſidered, that if any warrants were directed, for the apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of any that might be ſuſpected; the feare of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, might cauſe a more cloſe concealement: and therefore we purpoſed by private meanes to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme our ſelves, and to communicate each with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther what we could diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. But Sir <hi>Robert Howard</hi> (living then at <hi>Clunne</hi>) pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently granted out warrants, and thereby (amongſt other things) required a ſearch to be made in all lakes of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, pits, and other places, where in likelihood the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trified body might be caſt or drowned. And although
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:30840:60"/>this were a probable courſe being carefully mannaged, (as indeed it was) for finding of the body, yet neither was it found, nor any perſon thereby diſcovered for the fact. Then we all joyned our beſt endeavours in this diſcovery, knowing that the delinquents being once ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted, the body would ſoone be found. Having therefore received ſome private intelligence, of ſome perſons, who had commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the actors in this work of darkneſſe, and ſome alſo who had offered for ſome conſideration to effect it, we at length brought thoſe parties to examination, though therein we uſed the helpe of Sir <hi>Robert Harley,</hi> a juſtice of peace of <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi>
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:30840:60"/>Shire for the appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending of one of them, who indeed proved inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent. Sir <hi>Robert Howard</hi> and my ſelfe meeting at <hi>Biſhops Caſtle</hi> examined another, named <hi>Lewis Owen,</hi> upon whoſe examination, and teſtimony of witneſſes, there was evidence from his owne mouth, that he (at leaſt) had knowledge of thoſe that had taken down the body, though in truth (as it proved afterwards) in his drinke hee had ſpoken more then was true: but w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap> before the full truth appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, bound him over to the then next aſſiſes. Maſter <hi>Walcot</hi> and my ſelfe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded, (Sir <hi>Robert Howards</hi> occaſions then calling him to <hi>London</hi>) and upon exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:30840:61"/>we bound over another, by name <hi>Richard Williams,</hi> who had offered to <hi>Edward ap Evan</hi> the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of <hi>Enoch,</hi> that he would take downe his ſonne from the Gibbet, if hee would conſider his paynes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="section">
               <head>Sect. 23.</head>
               <p>By this time the judges of our circuit, Sir <hi>William Iones,</hi> and Sir <hi>Thomas Tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver</hi> had heard of the taking down of the body of <hi>Enoch,</hi> and they directed their let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, dated the eleventh day of <hi>October</hi> 1633, to the high <hi>Sheriffe</hi> of the County, and us the forenamed Iuſtices, requiring us to make dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent ſearch and enquiry, by
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:30840:61"/>our ſelves and all others, whom we thought fit to be imployd therin, whoare the Malefactors, and by whoſe abetment and privity the ſame was done; and to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme them of our procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding therein with all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient ſpeed, becauſe (as they expreſſed) they were to give an account of our proceedings. Although we were not conſcious to our ſelves of any want of dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, yet here is a further tye upon us, unto which we give all dutifull regard: and therefore, having by the former proceedings ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, that the actors were like to be ſuch, as for mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, or ſome ſuch reſpect, performed the worke; we proceed to the examination
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:30840:62"/>of ſuch neare friends of <hi>Enoch,</hi> as were likelieſt to give ſome reward. And in this number on <hi>Meredith ap Reece,</hi> who married <hi>Enochs</hi> ſiſter, tould us that his wife had intreated him, to let her make ten Shillings of ſomething that might bee ſpared, to pay her Siſter <hi>Margaret,</hi> according to her promiſe, to give to them that had taken downe her brother <hi>Enoch</hi> from the Gibbet. This being ſo far made knowne unto us, we often preſſed the friends of <hi>Enoch</hi> to diſcover the truth to the end there might nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuſpition, nor ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, light upon innocent parties: and called to their remembrance the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God already fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:30840:62"/>upon their family, and which were likely to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed further, if they or any of them, being actors or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bettors in this offence, by their concealing of it, ſhould cauſe others to ſuffer for it. Hereupon (this being <hi>Sater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day</hi>) we were intreated to ſtay our further examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on untill munday follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, upon which day it was promiſed, the three Siſters of <hi>Enoch</hi> ſhould diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover the whole truth. And according to this promiſe they came. The eldeſt Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, being <hi>Margaret</hi> the wife of <hi>Iohn Howells</hi> of <hi>Spoade,</hi> did then upon her examination confeſſe unto us, that ſhee being grieved and afflicted, not onely for the lamentable loſſe of her
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:30840:63"/>deere mother, and her only two brethren; but alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe her brothers body hanged upon the Gibbet, being ignorant (as ſhe ſaid) that it was an offence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the law, procured and perſwaded her two other Siſters to contribute with her in hiring a young man named <hi>Hugh Meredith</hi> (whom ſhee conceaved fit for that purpoſe, being of an able body, and a trayned Souldier in the band of Captaine <hi>Scriven</hi> before named) to take downe the ſaid body of <hi>Enoch</hi> from the Gibbet: which the ſaid <hi>Hugh Meredith</hi> (having pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured another fellow-ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier named <hi>Iohn Ieames,</hi> and another poore maſon to joyne with him) effected in
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:30840:63"/>the night time, and carried the ſaid body (being then putryfied) three miles upon a horſe backe, and buried it in a ſawpit, together with the cloaths and Irons. To this effect they al confeſſed upon their examinations, which are yet upon record remaining, with the clearke of the Aſſiſes, to which for more aſſurance I referre the reader.</p>
               <p>That nothing might be wanting for the diſcovery of theſe offenders, the Kings Majeſties counſell in the Marches of <hi>Wales</hi> alſo directed a commiſſion to certaine Commiſſioners, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well in <hi>Shropſhire</hi> as <hi>Mount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gomery</hi> Shire, for the fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding out of theſe Delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents: but before there
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:30840:64"/>could be any effectuall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding therein, they were diſcovered, bound to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare at the aſſiſes, and the foreſaid Iudges certified of our proceedings, who eft-ſoones acquainted my Lord Keeper therewith, as by their letters bearing date the 26. of <hi>November,</hi> 1633, expreſſing their approbati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our doings, more largely appeareth.</p>
               <p>Theſe perſons who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured the taking downe of <hi>Enochs</hi> body, or were actors therein, are all free from Puritaniſme, and ſo were conceived by the judges of aſſiſe, who as they were carefull to have the offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors diſcovered, as is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt by their letters, ſo when
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:30840:64"/>they appeared before them, they as diligently exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned them: but finding in them, fond affections joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with ignorance, and not any apparant wilfulneſſe, or factious contempt, in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeration of that diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and afflicted family, they ſpared ſeverity, and diſcharged them without further puniſhment: which they would not have done, if the offence had appeared to have beene committed by any Schiſmatical factio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts, as they publikely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="section">
               <head>Sect. 24.</head>
               <p>Surely Maſter <hi>Studley</hi> wanted ſome imployment
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:30840:65"/>in this diſcovery, for his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction to have made a more true relation; but he that preſumeth to lay this imputation to the judges (for it muſt needs taxe their Lenity and overmuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence to ſuch brethren of <hi>Enochs</hi> faction and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, as he ſetteth them forth to be) what will not he dare to ſay? Peradven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture he thought the juſtices of peace deluded the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, in the examination of the parties, and ſo made them appeare others then in truth they were: I that am one of them doe chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge Maſter <hi>Studley,</hi> to bring my actions, and theirs that joyned with me, to publike examination, and if we be therein faulty, let us
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:30840:65"/>not be ſpared. But if upon true tryall it appeare that the Author of the <hi>Looking-glaſſe,</hi> in his Epiſtle to the reader (as aforeſaid) aſſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us in the word of a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, that we have a relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſuch ſubſtantial truth, as he will maintaine againſt any perſon living upon the face of the earth; in this matter of ſubſtance, which hath beene examined in the face of the County, at the aſſiſes, doth deliver ſuch a manifeſt falſehood, who can believe him in any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing? Eſpecially, ſince hereby he caſteth the foule aſperſion of Puritaniſme, or non-conformity, not onely upon particular perſons that tooke downe <hi>Enochs</hi> body from the Gibbet; but alſo
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:30840:66"/>upon the honorable judges, and the juſtices of peace, as favourers of Puritans and Schiſmaticks. It may be he may apologize for himſelf, that the manifeſtation of this, and the examinations now upon record, were not to be ſeene when he wrote his booke: for his Epiſtle is dated the fourth of <hi>Septem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> 1633. I ſay it beſeemed his diſcretion, to have well informed himſelfe of the truth, before he caſt ſuch aſperſions upon any: but however his Epiſtle be da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as before, yet his booke came not to ſight in print in this Country, untill <hi>Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember</hi> 1634. before which time, there had two aſſiſes paſſed (after the execution of <hi>Enoch<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi>) which might
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:30840:66"/>have directed him by the proceedings therin, to have made a more true relation, or corrected his coppy.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="section">
               <head>Sect. 25.</head>
               <p>As Maſter <hi>Studley</hi> deales with thoſe before ſpoken of, ſo with others: as with the melancholy miniſter (pag. 40.) who did deprive himſelfe of his virilitie: and who (if I miſtake not his meaning) is yet alive, and therefore (in compaſſion of his infirmity) fit to be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted. I could wiſh he were as free from that hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, as hee is from non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformity. And ſo alſo with the layman of <hi>Tewx<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury,</hi> pag. 143. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> falſely
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:30840:67"/>accuſing him, and cenſori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly judging, the very thoughts of his heart in the particulars following, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt more that might be obſerved, as firſt, that he was twice Churchwarden, yet never was once. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, that he tooke down a croſſe, built in the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard. He medled not with the taking of it downe, but another workeman did it. Thirdly, that he placed the looſe Stones under the Church wall. He did not. Fourthly, that the ſecond time he was Churchwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, he tooke the ſtones a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. He begged a ſtone to make him a trough for a Grindeſtone, and a ſtone of the Croſſe being already hollow, and ſo fitteſt for his
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:30840:67"/>purpoſe, was given him by the then Churchwardens. Fifthly, that he cementing them together, made a Swines trough of them. This is falſe as before is ſaid, the ſtone being one, and hollow, his wife put Whey therein, and the pigges did drinke of it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was converted to that intended purpoſe. Sixthly, that the firſt meat his ſwine did eate therein, did drive them inſtantly into a raging madneſſe. The pigges were not mad, but wounded to death Seventhly, that the 2 next children that his wife (after he had taken downe the Croſſe) brought into the world, proved deafe, lame, and deformed, by monſtroſitie of body (and
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:30840:68"/>this) for his violation, and defacing of the ancient monuments of other mens devotion. If this befell him in his children (as it did not) yet it were a hard and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy cenſure. We ſee this known Antipuritan, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the ſecret cauſe of Gods judgements. Eighthly, that diſcovering, by the terrible teſtimonies of Gods wrath, the naughtines of his heart, in abuſing things dedicated to conſerve the memoriall of our Lord, and being o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome with tormenting terrours of a wounded ſoule, he leapt into a draw well, and was taken up bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and drowned. He was viſited with a purple fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor, then epidemicall in the Towne of <hi>Teuxbury,</hi> and
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:30840:68"/>Doctor <hi>Bave</hi> being conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, did foretel that through the violence of his diſeaſe, he would be diſtracted, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving warning to looke un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him: this advice of look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unto him being not fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, he aroſe, and went forth into a neighbours backeſide adjoyning, being the uſual wayto his garden, and hee was found drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in a well in the ſame backſid, whether by chance or choiſe, he came unto this end, to this day is uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine. I have ſelected theſe eight materiall falſehoods in this relation, and have ſet downe the truth after every particular, which I have taken out of a more large relation thereof, teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied to bee true under the
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:30840:69"/>hands of the Bayliffes, the Iuſtices, the Coroner, and the Churchwardens of the ſame towne, and pariſh, da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the 28. of <hi>October;</hi> 1634. to which for more full cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty I referre the reader. But upon theſe fictions Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Studley</hi> takes occaſion to vent his hearts griefe for many yeares ſuppreſt <hi>&amp;c.</hi> page 169.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="section">
               <head>Sect. 26.</head>
               <p>In like manner he dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth with Maſter <hi>F.</hi> in the latter end of his booke: wherein he himſelfe faileth in what hee would correct Maſter <hi>F.</hi> for; that is, in wiſedome, in honeſty, and in charity; for he publikly
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:30840:69"/>declared in his congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to his auditours, that he had beene credibly enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, that a very factious Sermon had been preached on fryday, before, in the hearing of them. It was wel known to al that heard him, who it was that had prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched the friday before, and ſo conſequently the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher knowne, though not named. Where was then Maſter <hi>Studleys</hi> wiſedome, in taking on truſt, and by information, a report ſo weighty without examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? Where his honeſty, in contempt of Maſter <hi>F.</hi> his perſon, whom he ought of duty to have privately conſulted? Or where his charity? Which is never ſuſpitious of evill before it
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:30840:70"/>be convinced by evidence of fact? The choyce of Maſter <hi>F.</hi> his text, ſeemeth factious to Maſter <hi>Studley:</hi> for the Lord <hi>Biſhop</hi> having preached upon the Text, 1 <hi>Pet</hi> 2.17. <hi>Feare God, and hon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ur the King.</hi> Maſter <hi>F.</hi> tooke his text <hi>Matth.</hi> 10<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 28. <hi>Feare not them which kill the Body,</hi> &amp;c. Now it is confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by Maſter <hi>Studley,</hi> that Maſter <hi>F.</hi> was wholy igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of the Lord <hi>Biſhops</hi> text, as is ſet downe pa. 281. nay hee was ſo farre from factiouſneſſe, that being im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portuned to preach, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſcant time for ſtudy, he preached the ſame Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, and upon the ſame text, which he had a Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day before preached in his owne pariſh. And therefore
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:30840:70"/>the Lord <hi>Biſhop</hi> (as he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe tould me) concerning neither errour in the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, nor factiouſneſſe in the manner of preaching, did order for full ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that Maſter <hi>F.</hi> ſhould preach againe at <hi>Shrewsbury</hi> and explaine himſelfe: which was performed, and the Miniſter ſtood in the <hi>Biſhops</hi> good opinion, as appeared by his commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of him to my Lord of Saint <hi>Aſaph.</hi> Yet after this courſe taken, Maſter <hi>Studley</hi> puts in print a letter (as he calleth it) of a ſharpe contents; and indeed it was very violent and virulent. unfit to paſſe between men of that order and ranke. Wherein hee taxeth that Miniſter of Gods word; as
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:30840:71"/>a falſe traducer, unwiſe, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honeſt, uncharitable, a ſec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie, a Schiſmatick, light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed, furious, fantaſticall, diſloyall, and unquiet, yet thoſe who know him (as I proteſt I doe not) ſay he is no ſuch man, but a modeſt, ſober, diſcreet, and confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable miniſter: and ſo my lord <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Lichfield</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived of him, as hee like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe tould me lately. The certificate mentioned in the letter, I have ſeene a copy of it, and of their names who have ſubſcribed it, who are of the beſt ranke and underſtanding in the Towne of <hi>Shrewsbury,</hi> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not ſuch as would certifie under their hands, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of a lewd and falſe report. They who
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:30840:71"/>heard the Sermon, and know the men, marvell at the impudency of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the <hi>Looking-glaſſe.</hi> And if the certificate, the Sermon, and the <hi>Biſhops</hi> cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, were printed as well as Maſter <hi>Studleys</hi> letter, the Reader no doubt would have full ſatisfaction. The letter it ſelfe of Maſter <hi>Studleys</hi> hand writing I have ſeene, and compared it with the printed: which is <hi>verbatim</hi> (as hee ſaith) without addition, detracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or mutation of one ſilla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: yet I have obſerved, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>an make appeare, above <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wenty variations of the printed, from the written letter it ſelfe,
<note place="margin">pag. 296 ſect. 54</note> but he that feares no mans tongue, what ſhould he ſticke at?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="section">
               <pb n="120" facs="tcp:30840:72"/>
               <head>Sect. 27.</head>
               <p>Hitherto I have laboured in the ſearch and diſcovery of the truth, and endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to free my neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood from the aſperſion of Puritaniſme or non-confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity: now my concluſion ſhall be, an earneſt requeſt to all good people, to make a right uſe of ſuch fearefull examples: not to be more profane, and to abſtaine from divine Service, the hearing of Sermons, hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and reading of Gods word, publicke and private prayer, becauſe they have heard, and read that this <hi>Enoch</hi> was a bould and bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy ſcripturiſt, that he would ride three or foure miles to
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:30840:72"/>heare Sermons, which is tearmed, the ordinary pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of this formal age, and yet he fell into theſe hay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous crimes: but rather to be more zealous, diligent, and conſtant, in the profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and practiſe of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity: and with all circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpection and fortitud, watch over our ſelves, and reſiſt the temptations of the fleſh, the world, and Sathan, by continuall prayer, <hi>Lord lead us not into temptation, but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver us from evill.</hi> The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of the parties murthered, and the partie murthering, will be ſpeciall motives hereunto.</p>
               <p>The parties ſlaine, were his mother, out of whoſe bowells he came, and from whoſe life, his life (next un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:30840:73"/>the Almighty Creator) was derived: and his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who came out of the ſame womb, and ſucked the ſame breaſts. Yet the lives of that deareſt Mother, and neareſt brother, were taker away, and by him, whom they leaſt ſuſpected, never feared: and even then when they were moſt ſecure. How great cauſe have we al, none excepted, of thankeſgiving to our good God for ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> preſervatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from ſuch a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den bloudy and cruell end of prayer, that our heavenly father would continue his gracious protection over us and to deliver us from ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine and violent death <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of preparation, for who knowes when that time will come, or in what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner we ſhall end our dayes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <pb n="123" facs="tcp:30840:73"/>Therefore by continuall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, faith, prayer, do<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing of good workes, let us prepare our ſelves, taking heed, leaſt at any time our hearts bee overcome, with ſurfetting, drunkenes, or the cares of this life, and ſo that day come on us unawares.</p>
               <p>If we conſider the party murthering, he was concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to be honeſt, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right in his dealing, free from drunkennes, or other notorious ſinnes (as farre as I can learne) hee was given much to reading and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, not onely privately and in his fathers houſe, but to frequent divine Service and Sermons. Now that God ſhould permit ſuch a man to fall into, and preſerve others in outward ſhew more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane and ungodly, from ſuch
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:30840:74"/>a bloudy crime; may mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter matter of wonder and amazement at the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God, which is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times ſecret and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found, yet alwaies juſt. And of terrour, leaſt he ſhould ſuffer us to fall ſo fearefully in the like manner.</p>
               <p>Laſtly if we conſider the religious duties which <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noch</hi> practiſed, as prayer, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the Scripture, fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenting of divine ſervice in Gods houſe: theſe are in themſelves good, &amp; ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily meanes neceſſary to ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; we are bound unto them by divine law, and the command of our Church and ſtate: ſhall we neglect them, becauſe he practiſing them fell into theſe ſinnes? Shall wee thinke that theſe
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:30840:74"/>were any cauſes of theſe murders? Shall we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne thoſe that are fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent in theſe holy actions? God forbid! The Scripture containeth the Goſpell, which is the power of God to ſalvation: let us read it. Prayer is the key of heaven: let us uſe it with our beſt devotion. The Church is the houſe of God, it is the place of his bleſſed pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence: let us frequent it. And by thoſe meanes, we ſhall be prepared for the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of everlaſting glory: wherein ſhall be no temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, no temptation, no ſinne, no ſorrow: but righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, peace, and fulneſſe of joy in the preſence of God, and preaſures for evermore. Vnto which eſtate the
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:30840:75"/>Lord in mercy bring us, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n the meane time keepe us from ſuch horrible ſinne.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="list_of_deponents">
               <p>
                  <hi>The true Copy of the ſubſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>on formerly mentioned, we whoſe names are under-writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten doe acknowledge that thoſe things in this treatiſe which have relation to us and our knowledge are truely ſet down and receaved from us, which we teſtifie by the ſubſcription of our names.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <list>
                        <item>HUMPHRY WALCOT.</item>
                        <item>THOMAS CLUNNP.</item>
                        <item>E. POVVEL <hi>vicar of</hi> Clunne.</item>
                        <item>GERVAS NEEDHAM.</item>
                        <item>WILLIAM BEDFORD.</item>
                        <item>ROBERT BARRET.</item>
                        <item>THOMAS HOVVELLS.</item>
                        <item>WILLIAM TANNER.</item>
                        <item>IOHN HOVVELLS.</item>
                        <item>WILLIAM GRIFFITHS.</item>
                        <item>IOHN LEVVIS.</item>
                     </list>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="appendix">
            <pb n="127" facs="tcp:30840:75"/>
            <head>An Appendix in further defence, of the precedent Relation wherein is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined Maſter Studleys pretended refutation of ſuch objections as were made againſt his Look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-glaſſe of Schiſme.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Gentle Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen I did firſt ſet my ſelfe to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Relation, I did not purpoſe to have it prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted (as in the beginning of my relation I have intimated) in regard whereof I had no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect in the framing of my diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to the ſwelling ſtyle
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:30840:76"/>which Maſter <hi>Studley</hi> pleaſeth himſelfe with in his Narration propoſing to my ſelfe onely a briefe diſcovery of the naked truth of the buſineſſe in hand; therefore marvell not that I have forborne to follow him in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll his deviations and imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent digreſſions: yet now my relation cometh to the preſſe unexpectedly I am urged to adde ſomething in regard of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſter Studleys additions to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he ſecond edition of his look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing glaſſe wherein he reciteth ten Criminations which I conceive to be all of his owne contriving, yet for the preſent admitting them by way of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply to Maſter Studleys an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweres I ſhall cleare ſuch paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages as from them ſeeme to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect on what I have delivered for truth.</p>
            <div n="1" type="refutation">
               <p>
                  <hi>The firſt Crimination is to this effect, That Maſter Studley hath publiſhed the moſt lying
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:30840:76"/>boooke that ever came forth in print.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Hyperbolicall part of this Crimination I maintaine not,
<note place="margin">Reply.</note> yet that his booke doth containe many falſehoods, I ſuppoſe it ſufficiently evidenced in thoſe inſtances given in the fiftenth and twenty ſections; and the twenty five Section de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clareth eight falſehoods in Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Studleys unneceſſary di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion to that of Teuxbury.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="refutation">
               <pb n="130" facs="tcp:30840:77"/>
               <head>The ſecond Crimination. Maſter Powell the reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Miniſter of Clunne under whom Enoch lived from his birth knowes many of your relations to be falſe &amp;c.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Aſter Powel had the view and peruſall of my precedent Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<note place="margin">Reply.</note> and find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it agreeable to the truth, of his knowledge he teſtifies, the integrity of this my Relation; by the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of his name: to that originall Copie, which now I have in my cuſtody, yea he
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:30840:77"/>was ſo earneſt in atteſtation of the falſehoods in this looking-glaſſe, that after he had ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, this relation in manner, and forme, as in the end there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is ſet downe; he deſired to be the meanes of conveying it to the Biſhop of Hereford, and did deliver it to his Chancelor, Maſter Docter Skinner, by whom it was delivered, to the Biſhop.</p>
               <p>Now let the unpartiall rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, judge whether Maſter Powell would deale ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthily with himſelfe, as to ſubſcribe his owne approbati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, of my Relation, and convey it to his Dioceſan, if hehad in deed ſo approved Maſter Stud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leys report; as is pretended.</p>
               <p>It is true that Maſter Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell is now dead, and leſt in that regard doubtfull thoughts may be entertained, with ſome men, I have heare inſerted a Certificate, from divers per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:30840:78"/>(of ſuch worth and credit, as Maſter Studley himſelfe, will not except againſt them) the Certificate, I ſet downe in the ſame words, as it was ſent unto mee, onely I adde the ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cification of their quality, and Condition for the readers bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſatisfaction.</p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="statement">
                  <body>
                     <p>Wee whoſe names are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, have heard <hi>Maſter Eraſmus</hi> Powell late vicar of <hi>Clun</hi> in his life time com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine of divers groſſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truths and falſities in Maſter Studleys Relation: of <hi>Enoch ap Evan,</hi> in his book intitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the looking gl. of Schiſme.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>
                           <list>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Humphrey Walcot eſqu.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Samuel Hilderſam Rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                                    <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                       <desc>•</desc>
                                    </gap>or of the Church of weſt felton county Salop.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Tho Clun of Clun Gent.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Hugh Edwards Gent.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Eſay Thomas Alderman of Biſhops Castle.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>William Tanner a free <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                       <desc>•</desc>
                                    </gap>urges of Biſhops Caſtle.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>George Lawſon Rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of the Church at the Moore.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Gervaſe Needham vicar of the Church at Biſhops Caſtle.</hi>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <pb n="133" facs="tcp:30840:78"/>
               <p>If opportunity had ſerved, or the cauſe required, futher proof might be produced, in like kind. For the preſent I further call to mind Sir Robert Harley Knight of the Bath. Walter Barker, of Hamond Eſquire, and Maſter Standley Gower Rector of the Church of Brompton Brian, who have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed me, that they heard Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Powell declare his diſlike, of Maſter Studleys booke in regard of the falſehoods there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in conteyned. And which is yet more, the aforenamed Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Barker, and Maſter Hilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam, were preſent, when Maſter Powell did to Maſter Studleys face tax him, for his untruthes in his booke.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="refutation">
               <p>The Third Crimination concerneth the taking downe of the body from the Gibbet: heere Maſter Studley ſweates to perſwade the reader, that he
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:30840:79"/>had ſtronger arguments to Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter his underſtanding then to believe that ſuch ſimple wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, as Enochs ſiſters, could be the chiefe abettors of ſuch a fact, five ſilly reaſons he reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, moving him to publiſh his conjecture that crafty heads contrived that deviſe of conveying his corps from the Gibbet, and breathed the ſame by inſtruction, and counſell into his ſiſters, Enabling there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ignorant women, of ruſtick quality and ſmall underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to take upon them, the mannaging of a deviſe ſo ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile and bold, who then were the authors of this deſigne, Maſter Studley telleth us in his looking-glaſſe, (Pag. 164. edit. 1) <hi>ſome brethren of his own dispoſition, and faction, reſtles in willfulneſſe, (that he might not ſay wickedneſſe,) contrived a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe by rearing up a ladder in the night, to ſaw off that part of the
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:30840:79"/>gibbet, where his body hanged &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As I will not affirme, but that ſome others might firſt ſuggeſt to Enochs ſiſter, the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king downe of his body, which they upon exam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nation, have denyed, ſo I hope no indifferent man wil ſuppoſe it to be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the compaſſe of womens underſtanding, to be guilty of hireing others to remove ſuch an object, ſo neere the place of their habitation and birth.</p>
               <p>I am to thank Maſter Stud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley, that he doth declare his beliefe, that the reſt of the Commiſſioners, with my ſelfe traveiled prudently, and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, yet he ſaith he neither doth, nor can, nor will believe that the totall truth was by us delivered, (for ſo hee ſaith in his refutation of Crimination, pag. 15.) for ſatisfaction of the Reader, herein I deſire him ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:30840:80"/>to conſider, the procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings againſt the offendors; as they are faithfully exhibited, in the twenty two and twenty three and twenty foure Secti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of my relation, to which I here adde <hi>(verbatim)</hi> that letter mentioned Sect. 23. From the Iudges, Sir William Iones, and Sir Thomas Trevor.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>
                           <hi>To the Right worſhipfull our lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving friends,</hi> Humphrey Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cot, <hi>and</hi> Richard Moore, Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires.</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>VVE receive your let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and thereby doun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand of the great care, and paines taken by you, for the diſcovery of that great affront to Iuſtice, in taking down the body of that notorious of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendor, <hi>Enoch ap Evan,</hi> and the burying of him, in an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure place, which we much commend and approve in you,
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:30840:80"/>for your induſtry therein, and ſo doth my Lord Keeper, unto whom we have made your care knowne: We alſo like well that you have bound over Enochs ſiſters, to the next Aſſizes, and doe deſire the Continuance of your care for the apprehending of thoſe of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendors, that were the actors in cutting of him downe, that their perſons may be ſent to the Gaole to remaine there till the next Aſſizes.</p>
                     <p>As for the body of <hi>Enoch,</hi> (which is much putrified, as you write unto us) we think it fit that it remaine in the earth, where it is untill you receive further directions therein.</p>
                     <p>And ſo thanking you both for your extraordinary dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence in this ſervice we com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit you to God and reſt,</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Your aſſured loving friends,
<hi>William Iones, Thomas Trevor.</hi>
                        </signed>
                        <dateline>
                           <date>This 26 of November. 1633.</date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="refutation">
               <pb n="138" facs="tcp:30840:81"/>
               <p>THe fourth Crimination I reject as unworthy the reciting, being framed out of an idle and frivolous imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="refutation">
               <p>The fifth Crimination, is ſufficiently maintained, in the twenty five Sect. which concerneth one of Teuxbury, in the County of <hi>Gloceſter,</hi> and is eagerly purſued by <hi>Master Studley,</hi> But he cannot free his looking-glaſſe from falſchoods, though he labour to excuſe it as no lye by a threefold diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and in that he received it upon report, yet <hi>Maſter Studley</hi> (perhaps to declare his unwillingneſſe, to forgoe his title of the <hi>Anti-puritan</hi>) ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his readi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſſe, to goe on to bring that matter to a further tryall upon the information of five inhabitants, of that Towne, (none of them named)
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:30840:81"/>what <hi>Maſter Studley</hi> preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth wil be ſufficiently pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by thoſe five men, is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicted, in that Certificate, dated 28. of October. 1634. and mentioned in the 25. ſection of the relation, being under the hands of the then Baylifes of Tewxbury, <hi>Chriſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher Canner,</hi> and <hi>William Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret,</hi> foure Iuſtices of Peace; <hi>William Hitches, Richard Bradford, Co. Richardſon,</hi> and <hi>Thomas <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aughan,</hi> the Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, <hi>William Hill,</hi> and the Church-Wardens, <hi>Edward Millichop,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Hate</hi> teſtifying the ſame to be true, in theſe wordes. <hi>Tho. Hicks,</hi> by profeſſion, a Slater, pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in his profeſſion, and thereby maintained a great charge in common repute, was a very honeſt juſt man, but never of ability, to be neere the place of a Church-warden in the corporation, or any
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:30840:82"/>other office whatſoever, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout ſixteen yeares ſince, the pariſh Church, being a goodly Abbey Church was much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired, wherin this poor man was many moneths imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and adventured his life in mending the roofe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, <hi>Hickes</hi> medled not with the Croſſe, but one <hi>Richard Kings</hi> another workeman, and yet living in this towne, tooke downe the head of it to place there a Sunne Dyall of value, being beſtowed by a skilfull mathematician, to give di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection for the ringing of the Bells to Service, and there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no other place, to place it, the Southſide of the Church being incloſed.</p>
               <p>This ſtone being thus taken downe, was put aſide in the Church, amongſt other refuſe ſtones, and <hi>Hickes,</hi> wanting a ſtone to make a Trough for a grindſtone, to whet his tooles
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:30840:82"/>did begge one of the then Churchwardens, who aſſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned him that particular ſtone as moſt fit for that purpoſe, being already made hollow, which he accepted and carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to his houſe, and he defer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to imploy it as hee inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, his wife put Whey into it, whereout young weaning pigges did drinke. Of this, complaint being made to one of the Bayliffes, he committed <hi>Hickes</hi> to priſon, and bound him to his good behaviour, and at the next Seſſions, upon examination of the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardens, and all other cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, he was diſcharg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the rather, for that it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared not what Images or Pictures had formerly beene ingraved upon the ſtone, but were many yeares worne out and defaced.</p>
               <p>And there it alſo appeared that the pigges which dranke
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:30840:83"/>the ſaid whey, did not runne mad, nor dye of any diſeaſe, but were mortally wounded.</p>
               <p>This was finally ended, and nothing thought or ſpoken of it, by the ſpace of about 12. yeares, but the poore man went cheerefully on in his calling as before, untill about three yeares ſince, the purple Feavour was then <hi>Epidemicke,</hi> and many families in the towne viſited therewith, and his amongſt the reſt, and his perſon in particular, in a vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent manner, in his ſickeneſſe Doctor <hi>Bave</hi> was conſulted, and did prognoſticate ſome diſtraction, as he hath certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied under his hand and ſeale: which (it ſeems) happened ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly, for the next day he went out of his houſe into a neighbours backeſide adjoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, being the uſuall way he went to his garden, and there was found drowned in a wel.</p>
               <pb n="143" facs="tcp:30840:83"/>
               <p>Hereupon a jury was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panelled, ſworne and charged, by his Majeſties <hi>Coroner,</hi> who having no evidence, how he came into the well, would have found an <hi>Jgnoramus,</hi> but being preſſed by authority for a more ſatisfactory verdict, they underſtanding what do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor <hi>Bave</hi> had ſpoken, and what others viſited with that diſeaſe, had attempted: found it ſpecially that by the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of the diſeaſe, being out of his ſences, he caſt himſelfe into the well. Yet many of the Iurors were threatned to bee bound over before the Iudges, before they would yeeld ſo farre as to determine whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he came into the well by chance, or choyce, voluntari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or accidentally and by the verdict he was freed from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing guilty of <hi>felo de ſe,</hi> neither were his goods loſt or forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. That this is true, the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:30840:84"/>before named, teſtified by ſubſcribing their names.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="refutation">
               <p>THe ſixth Crimination concerneth the ſuppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a love paſſage, the truth of which is ſet forth in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth ſection of the precedent relation, the omiſſion where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is in this crimination char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged upon Maſter <hi>Studley,</hi> or elſe he chargeth himſelfe ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, for I could never heare of any other Author of theſe Criminations, and ſurely a guilty conſcience is reſtleſſe, therefore having firſt accuſed himſelfe he proceedeth, and ſayeth <q>My anſwer is this; that divers prudent and ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious perſons, who had the overſight and peruſing of that ſinall treatiſe, did all concurre in judgement to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, that the imparting of that Relation would ſeem to weaken the ſtrength
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:30840:84"/>of the whole Narration: and leave in the mind of a heedful reader, ſome thought and ſuſpition that the rage of his love paſſion, had tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported his mind from a ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led temper, both of prudent conſideration of what hee intended, and from the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſence of naturall affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to his loving brother. This judgement of theirs (ſaith Maſter <hi>Studley</hi>) I muſt needs approve, and being a true concluſion na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally emergent from the manner of my expreſſion of that particular peece, for from a defect in my ſelfe, becauſe I was not willing in that place, to interrupt the Series and courſe of the Hiſtory, before the due place by my ſelfe aſſigned, for refutation of objections, the relation of that matter, which might ſeeme to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:30840:85"/>a repugnance and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariety to the maine ſcope of al my aymes, through the body of the diſcourſe, was thought fit, both by ſound judgement, and heed full circumſpection to bee ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Heere the reader may ſee plainely by Maſter <hi>Studlyes</hi> owne anſwer,
<note place="margin">Reply.</note> which I have recited in his owne words, that as the Lycencer of his booke, and his concurring <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>iends judged, it would wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the ſtrength of his whole Narration: ſo alſo himſelfe confeſſeth, <hi>that hee muſt needs approve their judgement, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a true concluſion, naturally emergent from the manner of his expreſſion of that particular peece.</hi> Surely there is little neede of any further diſcourſe, to demonſtrate to the reader, that <hi>Enoch ap Evan</hi> was ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to Lunacy. The appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:30840:85"/>thereof, ſo appearing to the diverſe prudent, and judicious perſons of Maſter <hi>Studleys Looking-glaſſe,</hi> that it moves them by <hi>ſound judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and heeafull circumſpecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to ſuppreſſe the paſſage</hi> of <hi>Enochs</hi> love paſſion, which might ſeeme to imply a repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and contrariety to the maine ſcope, and aymes of Maſter <hi>Studley,</hi> through the body of his diſcourſe.</p>
               <p>As little neede there is to diſcover, either the indiſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and weakeneſſe of Maſter <hi>Studleys</hi> apologie, or the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advertency of the Licencer of his anſwer to theſe Crimina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions if at leaſt it had any ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence at all. The concluſion then ſeemes to be this, that the maine ſcope of all Maſter <hi>Stud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leys</hi> aymes through the body of his diſcourſe muſt not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive any oppoſition or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction. He doth not here
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:30840:86"/>declare what his aymes are, but true it is, that in his Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to the Reader before his <hi>Looking-glaſse,</hi> he reciteth ſuch aymes for the furtherance whereof. I ſhall at all times, I hope, bee no leſſe ready then himſelfe, or any other, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute the uttermoſt of my abilities, and wherein they ſhall fall ſhort: my fervent prayers ſhall goe along with thoſe that with their greater abilities ſhall carry on ſo good aymes, as the glory of God, the honour of our King, the vindication of his inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent laws, and deſire of our churches tranquillity and peace; to theſe the Author pretendeth, and calleth God to witnes the integrity of his conſcience therein. I will not aſſume to my ſelfe, to be judge of that appeale of his<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But when I conſider the vehemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of his ſpirit, manifeſted
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:30840:86"/>through the body of his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, with the eagerneſſe of his reſolution to exhibit by this falſe glaſſe, an infamous badge on thoſe whom he tear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth Puritans, I cannot diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne it to bee any breach of the rule of Charity, to doubt of his pretended integrity, and conclude him guilty of premeditated defamation, of that profeſſion and thoſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons whom he tearmeth Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanicall.</p>
               <p>The truth of this will ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently appeare to thoſe, who ſhall diligently conſider the precedent relation, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare it with the Authors <hi>Look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-glaſs,</hi> wherein by way of review, I deſire the Reader to take notice of Maſter <hi>Studleys</hi> confidence, expreſsed in the 25, 26. and 27. Sections of both Editions of his booke, wherein he aſsumeth to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe the reputation, of the
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:30840:87"/>knowne <hi>Antipuritan</hi> of that County, and under that deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, boaſteth of himſelfe, and of his paynes, as having by his firſt argument (recited in Section 26) juſtly conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. That <hi>Sathan</hi> hath inſtiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a non-conformiſt, to as unnaturall, and bloudy a fact as ever was committed, and upon his ſecond argument Sect. 27. (he ſaith) the force thereof, is ſo cleare, concluſive and birding, that neither <hi>Enochs</hi> Non-conformed bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, wil accept or reject the word, (onely) the ſtrength of the thing affirmed remaines pregnant, dilucidate, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincible. The inſufficiency and vanity of thoſe his two arguments, I have ſhewed, (Sect. 13, and 14.) but what is that which Maſter <hi>Studley</hi> hath affirmed, I will not trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the Reader, with the repe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition of all the contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:30840:87"/>already noted here, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire him to take notice, that in the firſt Edition of his <hi>Look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-glaſſe,</hi> (pag. 160.) having in that 34. Section, diſcourſed of <hi>Enochs</hi> opinions, Maſter <hi>Studleys</hi> concluſion is, that he was neither <hi>Anabaptiſt, En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thuſiaſt,</hi> or of any other odde ſect whatſoever, but onely a ſilly ignorant and downright Engliſh Puritan, but in the Title of his firſt Edition, a downe-right <hi>Separatiſt,</hi> and then in the Title of the ſecond Edition of his booke, he tear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth him a down-right <hi>Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformiſt</hi> Surely Maſter <hi>Stud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley</hi> will find it a hard taske to free himſelfe in theſe variati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>om great vanity and giddineſse in his virulency a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his ſuppoſed Puritans, againe I deſire the Reader to peruſe the 38. Section of his <hi>Looking-glaſſe,</hi> in both Editi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons thereof, having in the 27.
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:30840:88"/>Section finiſhed, with <hi>Enoch</hi> the County priſoner, and now (ſaith Maſter <hi>Studley</hi>) <q>To vent my own hearts griefe, for many yeares ſuppreſt, and ſtifled in my troubled boſome, and a little to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large myſelfe, and to make knowne the quality of that people with whom I live: know good Reader (ſaith hee) that this Towne of <hi>Shrewsbury,</hi> the place of my birth, and reſidency, is great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly troubled with a ſect of men and women:</q> and ſo go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth on accuſing them of diſobedience to ſupreame Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, and of hate and detracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his perſon, with detri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and loſſe to his tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall eſtate. Now I ſuppoſe the Reader wil be perſwaded that I have done Maſter <hi>Studley</hi> no wrong, where alittle before I did conclude him guilty of premeditated defamation, of
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:30840:88"/>thoſe hee termeth Puritans. Againe conſider the tenour of Maſter <hi>Studleys</hi> Letter to Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Fiſher,</hi> who is known, and aproved to bee a grave and conformable Divine: the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry reading of which Letter, by any ingenious man, will ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the writer to be an inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Scurrilous Detractor, the letter was written upon a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, Maſter <hi>Studley</hi> heard that the ſaid Maſter <hi>Fiſher</hi> ſhould preach a factious ſermon, the proceeding of that buſineſſe is ſet forth in the 26. Section of the precedent Relation.</p>
               <p>Now conſidering the many repugnances and defamations of the Neighbourhood of <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops Caſtle,</hi> the judges of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſize, juſtices of peace, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther particular perſons, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned in Maſter, <hi>Studleys Looking-glaſſe,</hi> hee is to reſt thankefull to God and thoſe men whom he hath ſo tradu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:30840:89"/>if for his callings ſake, his perſon be permitted to keepe his reſidency, in quiet to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend his populous charge where I heartily with him comfort and peace, if he apply himſelfe faithfully to diſcharg the duty of a miniſter of Gods word, which is the ſtile he gives himſelfe, which if hee performe, he may find better arguments, and motives to reduce his neighbours to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity, then by charging up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, as he hath don in this his ſcandalous <hi>Looking-glaſse;</hi> which a Catholike Prieſt maketh uſe of, in a book called <hi>(Puritaniſme the Mother ſince the Daughter)</hi> where the <hi>Prieſt</hi> hath borrowed from Maſter <hi>Studleys Looking-glaſse,</hi> this fact of <hi>Enoch</hi> for an occaſion amongſt others of his writing that treatiſe, printed <hi>an. Dom.</hi> 1633. And ſo I leave the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to conſider of ſome better
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:30840:89"/>uſe to bee made of this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plored accident touched in the cloſe of the precedent re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="postscript">
               <head>The Poſtſcript.</head>
               <p>THere remaine <hi>4.</hi> other Criminations which Maſter <hi>Studley</hi> reciteth, I doe conceive they may bee juſtly objected a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him notwithſtanding what he anſwereth for himſelfe: but for as much as they ſeeme to bee framed out of a guilty conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and no way concerning the precedent relation, or any matter therein, J paſse them over with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out further reply.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>An Errata.</head>
            <p>Page 12. l. 15. dele. to p. 19. l, ult. on one p. 30. l. 9. r to the Barbour p. 35. l 12. r. Powderbache p. 30. l. 16. r. Sergeant, p. 41 l. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>2. r. onely p. 7. l. 1. r, ſuperſtitious p. 54. l. 20. r. inveigling p. 55. l. 18. r. that he anſwer p. 56. l. 16. r. in the miniſtery p. 76. l. ult. r. and at length p. 110 l. 8. r. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, p. 117. l. 2. inſtead of concerning read conceaving.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
